<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MarsBased</title>
    <description>MarsBased is an application development company in Barcelona, highly specialized in Ruby on Rails.</description>
    <link>http://www.marsbased.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.marsbased.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>The MarsBased Blogging Guide (Part 1)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d224.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the first part of the MarsBased Blogging Guide, where we will cover how to craft a good blog post, according to our standards. In the second part we will describe how to create a good blogging strategy for your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased we&amp;#39;re always learning new stuff. Running your own company means being constantly in the loop of learning things you could have never predicted you would ever need. Among other stuff, we have learnt how to run a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After over a year of blogging for MarsBased and other sites, such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupgrind.com/barcelona&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Grind&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://barcelonaventures.com/blog/&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Ventures blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona Ventures&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@lexrodba&quot; title=&quot;@Lexrodba Medium&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;my personal Medium&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#39;ve learned a thing or two that I wanted to share with all of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Choose a good title&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s start off from the very beginning: the title. Nowadays titles do not only have to be understandable by humans, but by robots too. And while we don&amp;#39;t refer to robots like &lt;a href=&quot;http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2014/2/21/1392977241047/Robot-from-The-Terminator-010.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Robot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://img4.wikia.nocookie.net/__cb20141005032524/deadliestfiction/images/e/eb/Optimus_Prime_Generation_1.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Robot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, it&amp;#39;s always a good idea to let Google bots and the rest of web crawlers &amp;quot;understand&amp;quot; that title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, if you&amp;#39;re writing a guide on how to craft good blog posts you might want to go with &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;How To Craft Good Posts For Your Blog&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;10 Useful Tips For Writing a Blog&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot;. Choosing a title like &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;Disentangling the Unfathomable Nature of Swordbuckling in the Interwebs&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot; probably won&amp;#39;t get you very far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titles should be meaningful, just like the first sentence of the post. &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.bufferapp.com/headline-formulas?utm_content=buffer144c3&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;utm_campaign=buffer&quot; title=&quot;Buffer blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Readers absorb the first and last three words of a sentence&lt;/a&gt;, so make them count. Also, avoid clickbait titles (&amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;I Unboxed My iPhone and I Couldn&amp;#39;t Believe What Happened Next&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot;) where possible. They&amp;#39;re not worth it: they might earn you a thousand followers today, but all will be gone tomorrow if you don&amp;#39;t deliver what&amp;#39;s promised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, but not least, titles should include your keywords. If you&amp;#39;re blogging about gadgets, include the words &lt;i&gt;wearables&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;tech&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;smartphones&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;gadgets&lt;/i&gt;, etc. This will help SEO and thus increase your blog&amp;#39;s visibility. Ideally, post titles &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.orbitmedia.com/blog/ideal-blog-post-length/&quot; title=&quot;Marketing tips&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;shouldn&amp;#39;t exceed 60 characters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Catch your reader&amp;#39;s attention&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first sentences of a post are crucial. As we stated before, they really do count to make a good impression and make clear what is the post about. They usually are the ones before the &amp;quot;Read more&amp;quot; button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post19a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Read more text&quot; title=&quot;Read more text&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Meerkat&amp;#39;s Medium account did pretty well here: placed their name, announced they&amp;#39;re an open platform and dropped keywords for developers.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the first sentences of a post count a lot for SEO, just like titles do. Some search engines will also index a snippet of the text, and that will be the first sentences. Also, when you share a blog post to Twitter or Facebook, a snippet of the text is included. Make the most out of it: keywords, facts &amp;amp; figures, a shocking anecdote...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, just like titles, the first sentences must be an open invite to click on the post and continue reading, while clickbait is strongly discouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Content&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the definition of good content is, as Guy Kawasaki put it, &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://startupgrind.com/guy-kawasaki-2015/&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind hosts Guy Kawasaki&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;content worth sharing&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can&amp;#39;t emphasize enough how important a blog is for SEO. A blog allows you to have original content (yay!), on a regular basis (double yay!) that can be commented and shared, and therefore spread through the web (triple yay!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, your company name will be spread throughout the web if you do it right. Choose your keywords wisely (don&amp;#39;t overbloat it, though!) and make it worth sharing. Then, your readers will do the work for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting tip: if you talk about companies or individuals in your post, it&amp;#39;s a good idea to link to their website. For the extra points, you can mention them in the social networks and maybe earn some extra retweets/likes/shares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we got started in the Internet, backlinking was a good idea. Back then, blogs and sites alike paid one another to have a link to their site, whatever the content was, just to pass onto one another visitors and pagerank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the reality is very different. &lt;a href=&quot;http://white.net/blog/high-risk-seo-33-ways-to-get-penalised-by-google/&quot; title=&quot;Google Penalises Backlinks&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google penalises that&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;#39;t have a dog in the fight, but we like to link other sites if we mention them. Not only to reference a quote, give other people credit, or also to help the reader find more interesting stuff outside of our blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that you don&amp;#39;t want your users to leave your page for good, so instead of adding a regular link to ease the transition from your blog post to an external website, just add the &lt;i&gt;target=_blank&lt;/i&gt; HTML attribute so that the new page opens in a new tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is likewise important to add a good title attribute to your link, to help crawlers and users alike to understand the nature of the link. In this case, if we want to link to &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.buffer.com&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&#39;s Blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Buffer&amp;#39;s blog&lt;/a&gt;, we&amp;#39;ll do it like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.buffer.com&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&#39;s Blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&amp;gt;Read Buffer&#39;s Blog&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our favourite bloggers, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.johnrampton.com/&quot; title=&quot;John Rampton website&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Rampton&lt;/a&gt;, who writes kickass posts for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.entrepreneur.com&quot; title=&quot;Entrepreneur-com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Entrepreneur.com&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://forbes.com&quot; title=&quot;Forbes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Forbes&lt;/a&gt; told us to use the first three links of a blog post to link your previous posts when possible. We didn&amp;#39;t find it suitable for this post, but most of the times it can fit in pretty well and will encourage newcomers to your blog to read your previous articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each blog post needs to have at least one image. Do not skip this part, ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images help readability and can help better explain a concept. Remember that &amp;quot;A picture is worth a thousand words&amp;quot;. Good examples of this are: a good infography, a picture of the crowded event you hosted or a nice shot of your new offices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images will also be fetched by RSS feeds and the sharing widgets of your favourite social networks, so make sure it&amp;#39;s well displayed there. As a matter of fact, Tweets and Facebook posts with images receive more engagement, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.bufferapp.com/twitter-images&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&#39;s Blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;according to Buffer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the tech side, images need to have their &lt;i&gt;alt&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;title&lt;/i&gt; attributes being as descriptive as possible. This will ultimately reflect on your SEO. Here&amp;#39;s an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&quot;http://route.to/image&quot; alt=&quot;A group shot of the MarsBased team&quot; title=&quot;A group shot of the MarsBased team&quot;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Readability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use subtitles to distribute the reading rhythm along the post. One long post with no subtitles is harder to follow; whereas a well-structured blog post with evenly-divided sub-sections will help maintaining the reader&amp;#39;s focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subtitles, when correctly marked using &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h2&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags, help crawlers index the page&amp;#39;s content much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perfect blog post length is thought to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bitrebels.com/social/makes-perfect-blog-post-infographic/&quot; title=&quot;Infographic about blogging&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;around 1200 words&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very important that you double-check your post thoroughly for typos, broken links, unformatted parts or unreferenced quotes. Mediocre or poorly processed posts seldom get shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this last case, remember what was the last blog post you read and thought &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m going to share this one&amp;quot;. Why did you do it? Was it the pictures? Was it funny? Was it because someone important wrote it? No. Most of the time you share it because you feel like more people should read it, and you either send it to specific people or you spread it on the web by sharing it through Twitter, Facebook or your social networks of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a good idea to re-read the post 3 o 4 times prior to publish, and it&amp;#39;s even more advisable to ask your team or another person to read it. What&amp;#39;s obvious to you, it might not be for everyone. A concept might need further explanation, some typos go unnoticed by spell-checkers (&lt;i&gt;your&lt;/i&gt; vs. &lt;i&gt;you&amp;#39;re&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;then&lt;/i&gt; vs &lt;i&gt;than&lt;/i&gt;) or you might have left a sentence unfinished (these things happen, but at MarsBased we alwa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Call to action&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the post should have a &lt;i&gt;raison d&amp;#39;être&lt;/i&gt;: it can be an informative post, a how-to guide, an opinion to give food for thought, or an invitation to the new beta version of your product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the aim of the post is, it should conclude with a call to action. A call to action (often referred to as CTA) is an instruction to the audience to provoke an immediate response, usually using an imperative verb such as &amp;quot;call now&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;find out more&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;visit a store today&amp;quot; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://homebusiness.about.com/od/homebusinessglossar1/g/Call-To-Action-Definition.htm&quot; title=&quot;Definition of call to action&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). If you don&amp;#39;t know what call to action do, the message of your post might not be clear enough, yet you can always ask the audience to share the post around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want an example of call to action? We&amp;#39;ll wrap up the post with one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you a blogger? What tips have you got that we might have skipped? Share your opinion in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/05/13/The-MarsBased-Blogging-Guide</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/05/13/The-MarsBased-Blogging-Guide</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lessons Learned: One Year Running Our Own Business</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d195.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time flies. We have been so busy this year, that we have barely had time to look back to all the things we have accomplished thus far. Actually, it’s been a year and a month since we legally founded MarsBased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the companies we look up to is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dockyard.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Dockyard&quot;&gt;Dockyard&lt;/a&gt;. They run a very inspirational blog, where they publish their experiences. This is a small homage to them and to &lt;a href=&quot;http://reefpoints.dockyard.com/opinion/2012/06/21/lessons-learned-six-month-of-running-dockyard.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Dockyard Blog&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post, where they described the difficulties they faced during the first six months running a consultancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we have learned in this first year of operating full-time as service providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post18.png&quot; alt=&quot;Keep Calm And Trust MarsBased&quot; title=&quot;Keep Calm And Trust MarsBased&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Keep Calm and Trust the Martians&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Market share&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first fears we had when we created the company was that there would be no demand for customized web apps in Ruby on Rails. Ruby does not have a big market share in Spain, so we had to create it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truth is, we have been overwhelmed by the incessant demand of Ruby development. Apparently, there’s not enough developers, nor specialized companies. We&amp;#39;ve also done a lot of technology-agnostic projects where we chose the tech stack. That means, we have contributed to increase the number of clients using Rails. You’re welcome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/strong&gt;: Identify the companies you want to work for and contact them or ask for an introduction. Most of them will want to hear your story. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep this section short, we will publish a dedicated post about each project we have completed throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Clients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clients are the essence of all consulting businesses. The difference between a successful company and a failed one often times boils down to choosing your clients right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good client can be your best asset: they talk about you, recommend you to other potential clients, give you more projects, promote your stuff, and offer better conditions over time. Actually, a happy client rarely ever changes providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, a bad customer can bring your business down. People that force you to work without contract, on abusive conditions or not paying customers pose a real threat to your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have defined your business model, and your company culture, you should also define what kind of clients do you want to have and stick to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accepting bad conditions now might seem a good idea if there are complicated months ahead for finding new contracts — such as summer, or Christmas time -, but it’ll prevent you from potentially finding a better client a little later in time (this is the so-called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opportunity_cost&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Opportunity cost&quot;&gt;Opportunity cost&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/strong&gt;: Before committing to any contract, find out what the opportunity cost is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Price&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important advise we can give here is: do not undervalue yourself. Not only because you will lose the opportunity cost (see above), but also because you are what you repeatedly do. That is, if your hourly rate is 70 euro, but you always offer friendly prices and end up working for 30 euro/hour, then you are a 30 euro/hour company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your strategy is competing with price, skip this section: we’re not a good example. But if you compete with quality, your high rates are more justified. Specialized companies/individuals charge more per hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, for one, started off at 50 euro/hour, which is actually cheap for a specialized company, but we wanted to build our portfolio. The market welcomed us with open arms with that price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we have raised our fee. We need to filter out the number of opportunities we get each month and we have a larger team now. Strange as it might seem, our ideal clients might not want to hire us if they perceive we are “too cheap”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/strong&gt;: do not start with a lower fee than you’d normally charge. Once you have got a client, it’s not easy to increase your rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Company culture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This. Is. Key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably because we look up to companies like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thoughtbot.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Thoughtbot website&quot;&gt;Thoughtbot&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://37signals.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;37Signals website&quot;&gt;37Signals (now Basecamp)&lt;/a&gt;, we always wanted to define a company culture for MarsBased right from the get-go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Company culture is one of the things we always review at our board meetings, or while talking to our employees. Most of all, we try to keep the Martian culture as present as possible in our daily grind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong and well defined company culture will help you take strategic decisions, for instance, when choosing projects or clients &amp;quot;is this client aligned with my vision?&amp;quot; or when hiring &amp;quot;will this person adapt to our company environment?&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/strong&gt;: Defining your company culture should be the first thing you do when creating a business. Then, make it evolve naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Methodologies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best things we have done, and feel more proud of, is having defined our own working methodology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have consistently identified workflows we incur in on a daily basis (or frequently enough) and turned them into a working methodology by identifying its bottlenecks and documenting where it was possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, our sales process was a bottleneck. Every time we needed to send an offer for a new project, the document had to undergo a revision by the whole team. More often than not, this revision was pushed back for over two weeks, potentially risking losing a customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identified this problem, analyzed it and found some solutions to this blocking issue. After the document is ready, the whole team has two days to do their revision. If no feedback is given, we assume everything’s OK and deliver the document. This way, if somebody needs to actually work on the document, he just needs to ask for some extra time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/strong&gt;: Find one day a month to step back and revise all your workflows. Identify issues and work on them. Rinse and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Hiring&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One year ago we did not expect to hire anybody before 2014 ended. At best, we could only hope there’d be enough work to sustain the three founding members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out we had enough work to hire &lt;a href=&quot;http://marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/18/The-MarsBased-Team-Grows-Bigger-The-Abduction&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Blog post about hiring Javi&quot;&gt;Javi&lt;/a&gt; in September, &lt;a href=&quot;http://marsbased.com/blog/2015/03/24/An-Internship-Out-of-This-World/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Post about Emilio&#39;s internship&quot;&gt;Emilio&lt;/a&gt; in December and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MarsBased/status/577401842105192448&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Xavier abduction into MarsBased&quot;&gt;Xavier&lt;/a&gt; in March, while outsourcing an additional 33% of our workload to companies like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.evilmartians.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Evil Martians website&quot;&gt;Evil Martians&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://mortensen.co/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Mortensen&quot;&gt;Mortensen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, hiring is not easy. As a consultancy, you need to focus on delivering results to your clients. There’s little to no time to do HR. We actually wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;http://marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/25/Dealing-With-Your-First-Hire-In-A-Distributed-Team/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Blog post about hiring&quot;&gt;blog post where we spoke about this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily enough, we have friends and colleagues that have recommended potential employees to us, and everyone we have hired so far turned out to be a really good asset to the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/strong&gt;: Hire only people you have worked with in the past or that you know very well. They will work harder to avoid disappointing you, and the risk of them being a flop is therefore minimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Delegate wisely&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principles we have built our company around is bootstrapping. We did not want to risk a lot of money in this, as it is our first company. So we decided to spend every penny wisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great at first, when you have enough time to deal with chores, while working on small projects (or even none of them). But as a specialized company, we needed to focus on what we do best: developing apps with Ruby on Rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we started growing, we found out that our workload increased as well. Thus, we began delegating some tasks to external companies. Bookkeeping was the first one, then legal stuff, and now we even delegate part of our development or some of our designs to companies of trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/strong&gt;: Always delegate stuff that is not imperative you keep in house. It might save you time, and time is ultimately money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Burnout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As first-time entrepreneurs, this is tricky to handle. The founding members entrance to the company was by working part-time on weekends and spare hours until we accumulated enough cash to employ all of us. It was a slow but safe process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, we would probably do it differently now. When half of your company is working full time, and the other half only on weekends and spare hours, working schedules might not overlap. Therefore, the part-timers drag the full-timers to work longer shifts (till late night) or even on weekends, when they’re not supposed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, stretching your working shift today will have an impact tomorrow. It’s easier to avoid burnout if you stick to your 40 hours work week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/strong&gt;: Define a clear roadmap for the incorporations and stick to it. Try to avoid the aforementioned situation by adjusting your schedules accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sales&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things we have had to learn so far is business development. Since none of us had a full sales background, we decided to have one person dedicated 100% to this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a full-time member focused on business development is something most early-stage development shops do not have. For us, it has allowed us to build a consistent image on the social networks, a blog, a good ranking on the search engines and a frequent offline presence (organizing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupgrind.cat&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona website&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Grind Barcelona&lt;/a&gt;, building the &lt;a href=&quot;http://marsbased.com/blog/2013/11/07/start-up-circle-barcelona/&quot; title=&quot;Blog post about Startup Circle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Circle&lt;/a&gt; community and attending an average of two events per week).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/strong&gt;: Sales are a service company’s fuel. Invest big time in this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Estimates, guesstimates and project planning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout this first year we have learned the cultural difference of working with Spanish clients and clients from outside of Spain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spanish clients prefer to work on a closed estimate of time and budget. A rather exhaustive document justifying how long will it take us to complete the project and a guesstimate in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truth is, project plannings change following users’ or investors’ opinions &amp;amp; needs, so this method is only fit for projects with a very clear and fixed scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, our clients from abroad prefer to work on a more agile way: we fix a price per hour and a number of hours per week and we start working. The project roadmap is built and rearranged every now and then during the length of the project, making it less of a hassle to change a functionality for another that was not in the original planning, thus allowing developers to focus on developing rather than doing estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/strong&gt;: So far, we have learned to work using both methodologies, but we don’t have a dog in the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What has helped us getting clients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order of relevance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organizing Startup Grind BCN and other events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing the &lt;a href=&quot;http://w153.bcn.cat/&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Happy clients referring us to their contacts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Belonging to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecommercetechbcn.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Ecommerce &amp; Tech BCN&quot;&gt;Ecommerce &amp;amp; Tech BCN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our referral agreement program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What has not helped us getting clients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following haven’t proved 100% useful yet when looking for new clients. Probably because we haven’t devoted enough time to them or because the timing or the execution were not right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cold emailing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Posting on LinkedIn groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using freelancing platforms (Workana, Elance, Freelancer.com…)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Other small lessons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s some other tips we have learned but do not deserve an own section:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always meet your deadlines. Clients will often not meet theirs, but that does not spare you from doing your homework. Be always ready for unexpected changes and to help your client.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previous experience in consulting and management have proved useful, specially when reporting to clients and managing expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treat your employees responsibly and they will behave responsibly (Basecamp&amp;#39;s Jason Fried &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inc.com/magazine/20091101/the-way-i-work-jason-fried-of-37signals.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Jason Friend&#39;s How I Work&quot;&gt;wrote about this first&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define a minimum budget for projects. You don’t want to waste your client’s time, so tell them what that price is upfront.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clients that don&amp;#39;t fit your company might be a right fit for others. Offer them to pass their contact onto companies/freelancers you trust. They will be very grateful for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you also run a company? Want to share some advise? Do it using the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/04/13/Lessons-Learned-One-Year-Running-Our-Own-Business</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/04/13/Lessons-Learned-One-Year-Running-Our-Own-Business</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Internship out of This World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d176.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I completed my degree in Software Development, to begin my career in web development, I opted to go for an internship. Turns out, a good friend of mine had attended the &lt;a href=&quot;http://marsbased.com/blog/2014/08/22/The-Martians-conquer-the-IronHack/&quot; title=&quot;The Martians Conquer the IronHack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;first Ironhack edition in Barcelona&lt;/a&gt;, where he met a couple of MarsBased members, and suggested that I applied for an internship there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is how I met MarsBased. Let me tell you how did it go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Landing on the red planet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my first day at MarsBased, they welcomed me as if we had known each other for a long time. That felt definitely relieving and took pressure off me, allowing me to learn much, work hard and make the most out of this experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working at MarsBased has definitely been radically different from what I had done in the past. For example, MarsBased is a remote working company, so we have no offices and work as a distributed team. I had no prior experience in working from home, but after trying it, I am now captivated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also found a company with a very solid company culture and clear goals. Everybody knows what these goals are, and what is the best way to accomplish them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For what I have seen, everyone brings in experiences from their previous jobs, so we all can follow best practices and avoid common mistakes. It&amp;#39;s all about the lessons learnt in the past. Sometimes you win, others you learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
Or simply put, using Rails, this is the &lt;strong&gt;MarsBased formula&lt;/strong&gt;:


&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;code&gt;[1] pry(main)&gt; positive_experiences - negative_experiences + ideal_company
[
    [0] &quot;marsbased&quot;
]&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
!--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this company, &lt;strong&gt;Martians are Martians&lt;/strong&gt;, not resources. We hold on this belief: however hard we may work, comradery is ever-present and there is always time for joking and laughing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Martian crew&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outwardly, MarsBased looks like a big company because of the huge workload we can cope with. In this case, however, size does &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; matter. It is the Martians&amp;#39; ability to organize and communicate that&amp;#39;s &lt;i&gt;from another galaxy&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is for sure one of the most important lessons I will take with me. Organization and communication are key in a remote working company. Both skills play a key role when dealing with client work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not a lot of rules in MarsBased, as strange as it might be. And the few of them we&amp;#39;ve got, they are really easy to follow, such as no emails, the weekly summary Basecamp post on Monday, simpler is better, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I wanted to highlight is the diversity among the team members. Despite being such a small team, there is a very diverse set of strengths and weaknesses that work like a charm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of all the previous points, we are a very friendly, transparent, responsible and social company, while being very powerful - technologically speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Adapting to the environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Mars, Ruby on Rails is spoken. Yet I came into the company with no prior knowledge of this framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every beginning is hard - they say - and mine was not an exception! Learning everything about routes, controllers, presenters, views, models and the rest of the jargon was not easy. It was all Greek to me. I came from a very different background, and although I could describe how to solve a problem, I wasn&amp;#39;t able to figure out how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that was not the worst. The red screen appearing after application errors, with a rather cryptographic error message scared the hell out of me more than once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few days learning prototyping using mockups and some layout from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/lexrodba&quot; title=&quot;Àlex Rodríguez Bacardit Twitter Handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Àlex&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/jordi_vendrell&quot; title=&quot;Jordi Vendrell Farreny Twitter Handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jordi&lt;/a&gt;, I have been working shoulder by shoulder with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/xavier_redo&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Redó Cano Twitter Handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Xavi&lt;/a&gt; most of my time in the company. He has been my guide in this journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xavi is a natural born teacher. He is very good at explaining why things happen the way they do. Not only that: he&amp;#39;s extraordinarily gifted in keeping a clear discourse when he&amp;#39;s explaining technical concepts. Talking to Xavi feels like talking to an encyclopedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, Xavi has been more than a teacher: he&amp;#39;s also taught me how to avoid burnout, praised my progress and cheered me up in those hard days when you can&amp;#39;t tell an Array from a Hash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Back to Earth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Mars there is no oxygen, and my reserves are now depleted. I have to keep learning how to survive in such an environment, and that will happen somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;... or it might just be that I have not overcome my addiction to nachos with guacamole. You can&amp;#39;t find them on Mars, so I am coming back to the blue planet to refill my reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a farewell. It is more like a &amp;quot;see you later&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you very much for the ride!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- Emilio&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased team during Christmas Dinner 2014&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased team during Christmas Dinner 2014&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Good luck with your new endeavour, Emilio! We&amp;#39;ll miss you!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/03/24/An-Internship-Out-of-This-World</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/03/24/An-Internship-Out-of-This-World</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our New Year&#39;s Resolutions for 2015</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d114.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2014 has been an amazing ride. It has seen us creating MarsBased, getting our first small projects, speaking at conferences, getting big projects, mentoring at IronHack, working for the Barcelona City Council, leading Startup Grind &amp;amp; Startup Circle, welcoming our first hires and many other amazing achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, we&amp;#39;re preparing a detailed review of 2014 for you all to enjoy and discover what&amp;#39;s been going on in the MarsBased spaceship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the 2014 post is being baked, we&amp;#39;ll share with you our new year resolutions for this promising 2015!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our first meeting of the year, everybody was asked what his resolutions for 2015 were, both personal and professional. Most of the resolutions are strongly related to our first months at MarsBased and/or our previous jobs, so we will be providing a little background to help you understand our resolutions better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not only help us bonding with each other, but it is also part of our new strategy of publishing more blog content and providing more transparency as a company (inspired in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://buffer.com&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Buffer&lt;/a&gt; guys, who are doing a terrific job at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bufferapp.com/transparency&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&#39;s Transparency policy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;helping new companies delving into corporate transparency&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In no particular order, here&amp;#39;s what the Martians pledged to achieve in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Xavier Redó - CTO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xavi started the year joining his previous company, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opscaling.com/&quot; title=&quot;GNuine&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GNuine&lt;/a&gt;, because we didn&amp;#39;t know we&amp;#39;d be able to recruit him so early. Our best guesstimates assumed we&amp;#39;d have to wait until the end of the year to have him working full-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past year has seen Xavi working hard to cope with all the projects we&amp;#39;ve gotten at MarsBased, therefore his resolutions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/xavi-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Xavier Redó&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Redó&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Xavier Redó&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CTO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Technologically speaking, I would like to be able to invest more time in exploring new technologies and frameworks to help us face the constant request of mobile apps.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Secondly, I would like to identify repeating patterns in our development processes in order to extract libraries we can reuse in the forthcoming projects and open source them when possible.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Leaving tech aside, I would like to participate more in events and conferences. I think I can add value in initiatives whose goal is to provide formation to new developers.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Actually, I can also provide interesting content online, so I will be contributing more to the MarsBased blog. We&#39;ve gathered some interesting results in 2014, and I would like to publish them and share them with our followers and the Rails community.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Finally, something I would like to improve is my time allocation skills. I am pretty accurate at guesstimating all the needed resources for each project, but so far I haven&#39;t included all these side-projects into my agenda. Here&#39;s to a 2015 for improvement!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Emilio Ríos - Developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emilio joined us barely a month and a half ago. But in our eyes, feels like he&amp;#39;s been with us for all the ride. He is, however, combining his internship at MarsBased with finishing his studies at La Salle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote right-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/emilio-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Emilio Ríos&quot; title=&quot;Emilio Ríos&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Emilio Ríos&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Developer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Since I have not been programming for long - at least not professionally - I would like to commit to improve my programming skills in 2015. Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://ejohn.org/blog/write-code-every-day/&quot; title=&quot;Write Code Every Day&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Resig&lt;/a&gt;, my new year resolution is to produce code every day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Now that my team-mates depend on me, I want to learn as much as possible to be helpful to them!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Javier Pérez - Developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javi joined MarsBased at the beginning of Q4, in early October. Having worked at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vass.es&quot; title=&quot;VASS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VASS&lt;/a&gt; together with Àlex, he transitioned from a full-time corporate J2EE consultant to an AngularJS/Rails developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same as Emilio, feels like he&amp;#39;s been forever with us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/javi-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Javier Pérez&quot; title=&quot;Javier Pérez&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Javier Pérez&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Developer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I would like to master Rails in the coming months so that I can be 100% autonomous in the projects I am assigned to. This way, I will also be able to explore new techniques &amp; trends on my own.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;By acquiring more knowledge on Rails, I will be able to spot recurring patterns that I can turn into libraries for our projects.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;On a personal side, and when I will be more autonomous, I would like to travel more. I want to enjoy this freedom of schedule we&#39;ve got and visit places I haven&#39;t been to!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Last, but not least, I would like to keep my condition of being single :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Àlex Rodríguez - CMO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started 2014 in San Francisco, having then recently quit my previous job at VASS, where I worked with Javi - actually, we were in the same project, sitting next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some weeks wandering around the city-cradle of entrepreneurship, I returned to Barcelona and got the Barcelona Startup Map project. That gave us the opportunity of employing me full time at the end of Q1, despite the fact that we were bootstrapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are my resolutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote right-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/alex-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Àlex Rodríguez&quot; title=&quot;Àlex Rodríguez&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Àlex Rodríguez&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CMO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;2014 was a year of working hard to meet all the deadlines &amp; cover all the areas of creating a company. I balanced my area&#39;s tasks (sales/marketing) with all sorts of other operational tasks to keep the development team focused.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This year I want to work smarter by focusing on my own areas (sales/marketing), while helping others improve in theirs.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Also, in terms of pushing my marketing skills to the next level, I want to learn graphic edition as well as improve my writing skills, publishing blog entries more often.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In terms of achievements, I would like to land a couple of big projects this year (if possible, from abroad). Also, I will be devoting more time to our presence in events, besides strengthening our relationship with Startup Grind &amp; Startup Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Jordi Vendrell - COO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordi is the third founding member at MarsBased. However, due to his duties as a Technical Director at Green Data and having a child last year, he couldn&amp;#39;t join MarsBased until now. He&amp;#39;s joining full-time on February, 9th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year he spent it balancing his position at Green Data, some hours during the weekends for MarsBased and his condition of first-time father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/jordi-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jordi Vendrell&quot; title=&quot;Jordi Vendrell&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Jordi Vendrell&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;COO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I only ask that on 2015 I will be able to combine professional and personal life better: spend more time with my family, get fit and keep doing a great job.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;As for MarsBased, I would like to produce a new version of our corporate website that stands up to our status nowadays. It has to be a kick-ass website! Also, I&#39;m looking forward to being more involved in the operative work of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;... and you? What are your resolutions for this year? Share them in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/01/20/Our-New-Years-Resolutions-For-20154</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/01/20/Our-New-Years-Resolutions-For-20154</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our First Christmas Dinner</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d87.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s been two months since our last status update, and we wanted to let you know we&amp;#39;re far from dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a fledging progression that has seen us completing our first projects after the summer, a couple of new big challenges have popped up. All these projects have kept us swamped with work, but they are also a reason to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, 2014 has brought many good achievements and landmarks for our company. But none of them can compare to celebrating our first Christmas dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A year in review&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MarsBased spaceship has been working at full capacity to complete the ongoing projects we have had thus far, having barely no time to update the blog. While we can&amp;#39;t wait to tell you everything we are undergoing at the moment, we also need to meet the deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s review the steps we have taken to reach this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MarsBased as a company was founded in March this year, after I came back from San Francisco. Signing all the required documentation to create the company was both relieving and challenging, and definitely has changed our lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing some minor projects, we got the opportunity of working for Barcelona Activa, in the creation of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bcn.cat/bcnstartupMap&quot; title=&quot;BCN Startup Map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/a&gt;. This project gave us enough propulsion (both economically and visiblity-wise) to start working on other projects. Also, through this project we were contacted by other companies who wanted to hire our services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the summer we landed the project of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eureka-startups.com&quot; title=&quot;Eureka Startups&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Eureka Startups Experts&lt;/a&gt; (still in progress), and a couple of other projects, that allowed both Xavi and I to go full time for the company. As a result of that, we boosted our production capacity, which means we could take on more &amp;amp; bigger projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working full-time, we could also start going to events, thus increasing our visibility in the scene. We participated in numerous events, organizing meetings with the Startup Circle, collaborating with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupgrind.cat&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Grind&lt;/a&gt;, mentoring at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ironhack.com&quot; title=&quot;IronHack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IronHack&lt;/a&gt;, giving speeches at congresses, attending &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.baruco.org&quot; title=&quot;Baruco&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Baruco&lt;/a&gt;, and meeting fantastic people everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was in September-October that we landed a couple of big projects from abroad (details to be disclosed soon!). These two projects have given us enough stability to hire &lt;a href=&quot;http://marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/18/The-MarsBased-Team-Grows-Bigger-The-Abduction/&quot; title=&quot;Our blog post of our first hire&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Javi&lt;/a&gt; to increase our development capacity again. Soon thereafter, we got the opportunity of welcoming our first intern &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MarsBased/status/538760313836158976&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased welcomes Emilio Rios&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Emilio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A Martian Christmas dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Wednesday we got together and spent a whole evening celebrating the first MarsBased Christmas dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a remote working company, this kind of get-togethers are essential to help bonding with the team at a personal level. They also increase happiness in the company and provide a good way to talk about stuff that&amp;#39;s normally not covered in the corporate chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evening started at &lt;a href=&quot;https://foursquare.com/v/la-cerveseria-clandestina/50447f7de4b072dc97475858&quot; title=&quot;La Cervecería Clanestina&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cervecería Clandestina&lt;/a&gt; to taste a selection of the finest beers. Barcelona is not famous for its craft beer yet, but it&amp;#39;s a growing trend that is getting very popular in the last years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post15a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased team at Cervecería Clandestina&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased team at Cervecería Clandestina&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Beer makes people more proficient in foreign languages such as Martian!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dinner took place in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://foursquare.com/v/lomb%C3%BA/4c0ab162009a0f475fe1e9bf&quot;title=&quot;Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Restaurant L&amp;#39;Ombú&lt;/a&gt;. A very cozy restaurant hidden between the Gracia and Horta districts in Barcelona. A well-kept secret for fusion cuisine mixing tradicional Catalan recipes with the latest trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post15c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Enjoying tasty Earth food at Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; title=&quot;Enjoying tasty Earth food at Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Enjoying tasty Earth food at Restaurant L&amp;#39;Ombú.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post15d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased team at Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased team at Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;The MarsBased team at Restaurant L&amp;#39;Ombú.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the restaurant we spent hours talking about the company and its future, and we toasted to our success in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evening came to a close at the famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://foursquare.com/v/elephanta/4b510121f964a5201a3d27e3&quot; title=&quot;L&#39;Elephanta&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;L&amp;#39;Elephanta&lt;/a&gt;, one of the best gin&amp;amp;tonic places in Barcelona. Conversation drifted to off-topic mode and provided an excellent ending to a lovely evening out enjoying a good share of teambuilding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post15e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased team at L&#39;Elephanta&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased team at L&#39;Elephanta&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Martian advise: Don&amp;#39;t drink &amp;amp; drive spaceships.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are ecstatic to have been able to celebrate such a landmark in our career and looking forward to kicking off 2015 stronger than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy &lt;code&gt;I18n.translate :local_winter_celebration&lt;/code&gt; everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2014 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/12/23/Our-First-Christmas-Dinner</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/12/23/Our-First-Christmas-Dinner</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dealing With Your First Hire in a Distributed Team</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d30.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last blog entry we described our first day with our new hire, Javi. Two weeks in, and the whole team has felt the boost of having a new employee at MarsBased: the company is producing more, he&amp;#39;s learning while having fun, and so are we.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a new employee brings in a whole set of risks that need to be adressed when running your own company. One of them is the integration in the team, and this is what this entry is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re talking about our first employee here. &lt;i&gt;Serious business&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having read a lot of literature on how to deal with this situation, we found these tips worth sharing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Day to day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When introducing a new hire to your company, you need to make sure he feels integrated as soon as possible, specially in small companies. And even more so if he/she is your very first hire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most valuable piece of advice here is &lt;i&gt;work naturally&lt;/i&gt;. 37Signals&amp;#39; book &lt;a href=&quot;http://37signals.com/remote/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Remote: No Office Required&quot;&gt;Remote: No Office Required&lt;/a&gt; strongly advises companies to continue working like they did before the employee was hired. Changing your behaviour will look like unnatural and will create awkward situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be yourselves while making him part of team decisions, not leaving him out of meetings, and showing him everything is there to learn. Obviously, you&amp;#39;ll be spending some time teaching him all that stuff, but consider this as an investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, terms like &amp;quot;family&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; should be avoided. After all, this is a business relationship. Experts tend to favour the usage of expressions such as &amp;quot;we&amp;#39;re a team&amp;quot;, instead. Or else, no mentioning of this at all. &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.hbr.org/2014/06/your-company-is-not-a-family/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Your Business Is Not A Family&quot;&gt;This blog post&lt;/a&gt; explains the situation very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line here is: show, don&amp;#39;t tell. Your actions will be more valuable than your words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Roles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distributed teams meet seldom. In these companies, the limits of your duties and/or responsibilities are sometimes unclear. Specially if the introduction to the company isn&amp;#39;t done right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue can be avoided by introducing the team accordingly, and telling the new hire clearly what you expect from him or her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, when hiring a new programmer, do not send him into coding without explaining what&amp;#39;s your coding style, which metodologies do you use, whether you do pair programming or not, which technologies do you expect him to know, the frequency of your commits, what additional tasks will he have to handle (devops, code refactoring, QA, performance tests, etc.) and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these situations, it is better to tell them what they are expected to do according to their role, but that they set the limits to their involvement with the company. That is: programmers deal with the development of the apps, but they have the option of getting involved with social media, writing in the blog, participating in the sales processes, improving internal organizational processes, preparing workshops for events, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides that, in small teams, the figure of the leader - bosses who work by your side - is enforced, instead of the classical boss enclosed in his own office. An almost-flat hierarchy helps easing this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post14.png&quot; alt=&quot;Remote: No office required&quot; title=&quot;Remote: No office required&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://37signals.com/remote/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Remote: No Office Required&quot;&gt;Remote: No Office Required&lt;/a&gt; is one of our favourite books and a mandatory read for distributed teams.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Communication is key&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending half a day listing all the communication tools you use as a team, and how to use them, is never a waste of time. On the contrary: set the rules now, and forget about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://basecamp.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Basecamp&quot;&gt;Basecamp&lt;/a&gt; for internal discussion that needs to be recorded. Then we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://slack.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Slack&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt; for in-real-time communication and having the water-cooler effect of always having someone to talk to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hardly ever email each other save for communications with third parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it is very important to present all the tools to the new hire, as well as the frequency of use and some rules that need to be met to ensure a fluid &amp;amp; correct communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Get-togethers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, get-togethers, for work or leisure, are necessary in all remote working companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a team that never sees each other&amp;#39;s faces save for videocalls. As hard as they might try, there&amp;#39;s a great chance they will not bond as much as a normal company due to the lack of physical connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In distributed teams, not everybody lives in the same city. In some cases, you might even have an employee in the other side of the globe, that might probably feel a little left out if not dealt with properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get-togethers help bridging that gap. They create a sense of bonding that should be enforced regularly, depending on the maturity and budget of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, get-togethers for working will also boost productivity for a day. Instead of everyone working separately, try getting the team together in the same room for a day. This will boost creativity and create an exciting vibe to get more stuff done before the session ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, get-togethers on the new employee&amp;#39;s first day are also critical to help easing the introduction to the rest of the crew. He or she will want to meet the bosses &amp;amp; coworkers on the first day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the company side, that shows appreciation and interest in the new employee. Not only will this help him/her gelling in with the rest of the crew, but they can all get to know one another in a more natural way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your company a distributed team as well? Feel free to share your tips and experiences with us in the comments below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/25/Dealing-With-Your-First-Hire-In-A-Distributed-Team</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/25/Dealing-With-Your-First-Hire-In-A-Distributed-Team</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The MarsBased Team Grows Bigger: The Abduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d23.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, October 7th will be a date to remember for all the Martians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last few months we have been swamped with work. Far from being a quiet and relaxed summer, the MarsBased flagship has been advancing at cruise speed. And to face the coming months, we hired a new developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s what we did in our first day with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;In the last chapter of The MarsBased Diaries...&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the summer we have been working non-stop to make MarsBased grow bigger, looking for larger projects that would allow an organic and sustainable growth of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out, one of the first contacts we ever made as MarsBased reached out and hired us for a very ambitious project we hope to disclose very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is big. So big that &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/xavier_redo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Redó Twitter handle&quot;&gt;Xavi&lt;/a&gt;, our CTO, could not complete it on his own in the given dates. So we hired a new Martian called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/_iamjavi_&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Javi&#39;s Twitter handle&quot;&gt;Javier Pérez&lt;/a&gt;, who has an extensive background in IT consulting and webapps development. Plus he&amp;#39;s got a beard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Abduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we&amp;#39;re a remote working company, we do not have a physical office. We always meet our clients at their offices and seldom hold any get-togethers by now. So we went out for some coworking at one of the best venues in town: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.start2bee.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Start2bee coworking space&quot;&gt;Start2bee&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javi is our first hire at MarsBased, so we made sure we gave him the best possible welcoming to the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He showed up with his new &amp;amp; shiny Macbook Pro and after having read the Martian Playbook, prepared for a day-long session of initiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post13a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MarsBased abduction&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased abduction&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;MarsBased corporate presentation to commence the abduction!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session kicked off with a formal presentation of the company: who we are, what are our working methods and what do we offer as a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then reviewed the MarsBased Playbook to emphasize the importance of communication and mutual understanding in distributed teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the first half of the coworking session ended with a review of the company history, project by project, to help understand our progress as a company up until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch, we started rolling: Xavi and Javi teamed up to start pair-programming while the rest of the team worked on project definition and estimations for potential clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Immediate future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our biggest challenge is to integrate Javi into the MarsBased culture &amp;amp; working methods as soon and natural as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His challenge is to help us achieve the goals we&amp;#39;ve set, that we couldn&amp;#39;t achieve without him, while bringing a whole lot of expertise in Javascript to our tech stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for that, he (also) got a corporate coffee mug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post13c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MarsBased coffee mug&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased coffee mug&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;MarsBased coffee mug with our new logo!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome aboard, Javi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: Xavi and Javi will be pair-programming during the next weeks at Start2bee a couple of days a week. Drop by to say hello, if you&amp;#39;re around!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/18/The-MarsBased-Team-Grows-Bigger-The-Abduction</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/18/The-MarsBased-Team-Grows-Bigger-The-Abduction</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Martians Conquer the IronHack</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d636.y35/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we created MarsBased, we decided to be a social, outgoing and media-friendly company. We also wanted to help the community, to pay back what the community had helped us in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early stages of a company, this is however something hard to achieve. The first priorities should be creating the company, establishing an organized accounting culture and sales, and developing your product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the cash comes in, and stabilizes the company, you can take some time to contribute back to the community. While it&amp;#39;s not mandatory, it clearly helps developing a friendly attitude as a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, we have been helping newcomers in the Ruby community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Enter the IronHack&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we created the company, we compiled a list of the leading Ruby development shops we wanted to meet and learn from. We threw in a bunch of names such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://thoughtbot.com/&quot; title=&quot;Thoughbot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thoughtbot&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codegram.com/&quot; title=&quot;Codegram&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Codegram&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://plataformatec.com.br/&quot; title=&quot;Plataformatec&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Plataformatec&lt;/a&gt; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last December, when I embarked in &lt;a href=&quot;http://startupoddity.ghost.io/meeting-san-francisco/&quot; title=&quot;Startup Oddity Blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;my trip to San Francisco&lt;/a&gt;, I reached out to the all of them and got a fair share of replies, hence meeting the guys from &lt;a href=&quot;http://thoughtbot.com/&quot; title=&quot;Thoughbot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thoughtbot&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://monterail.com/&quot; title=&quot;Monterail&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Monterail&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://prorubyteam.com/&quot; title=&quot;ProRuby&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ProRuby&lt;/a&gt;, just to name a few. All of them vowed to help us like they had been once helped, and gave us very useful pieces of advice. It was, indeed, a very promising start!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also added to the list some developer bootcamps, completely ignoring the fact that most of them work exclusively with top-class companies and developers. However, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ironhack.com/&quot; title=&quot;IronHack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IronHack&lt;/a&gt; replied back nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Time Flies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some months of chatting back and forth, I received an email from them asking for collaborators for their summer edition in Barcelona. We were invited to know them in person, at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mob-barcelona.com/&quot; title=&quot;Makers of Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MOB&lt;/a&gt;, and introduced to their team assistants and guest teachers: top Ruby and Javascript developers, working for Xing, Spotify and other leading companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IronHack bootcamp runs for two months with full dedication to learning coding: Rails, AngularJS, Javascript and what it takes to create state-of-the-art webapps. After their daily dose of programming, the session is completed with talks regarding different subjects: branding, accounting, marketing and all kinds of useful stuff. We were asked to provide two talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;First Talk: Create your Company NOW&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was honoured to give the first talk of the current edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I know that most people there are passionate about web applications and will end their IronHack program creating an app (because it&amp;#39;s their final project), I thought it would be useful to motivate them. What if they didn&amp;#39;t only program that app for IronHack? What if they could create a startup around it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Prezi to create a motivational presentation using their fantastic Space template (fits perfectly with our Martian imagery) and rallied the troops to go out and create their startup right NOW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post12a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Àlex presenting at IronHack&quot; title=&quot;Àlex presenting at IronHack&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Warning! The presentation contains profanity!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://prezi.com/ttqvo8ssl6ew/create-your-company-from-out-of-this-world/&quot; title=&quot;Prepare your business to sky-rocket&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Get the presentation here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Second Talk: Bulding Large Webapps That Are Easy to Maintain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later, Xavi provided a largely comprehensive talk on how to build large web applications to be easily maintainable. While the presentation dealt mostly with Rails best practices, it contained a fair share of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=lulz&amp;defid=2539255&quot; title=&quot;Definition of lulz&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lulz&lt;/a&gt;. At MarsBased we enforce the use of meme-driven presentations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post12b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Xavi presenting at IronHack&quot; title=&quot;Xavi presenting at IronHack&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Meme-driven technical presentation!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/12625879/MarsBased/Ironhack%20presentation.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Bulding Large Webapps That Are Easy to Maintain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Get the presentation here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback we received was so good that we were invited to an afterwork event on the rooftop of Betahaus, where we talked everything: from loving or hating TDD, to everyone&amp;#39;s future plans or why Barcelona is the best city in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We definitely connected with the IronHack community and want to get more involved in the coming editions to make more people love coding and Ruby on Rails. So far, we can say we will be mentoring at the next edition of IronHack in Barcelona!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you meet us at IronHack? We would appreciate if you left some feedback in the comments section!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love from Mars.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2014 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/08/22/The-Martians-conquer-the-IronHack</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/08/22/The-Martians-conquer-the-IronHack</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sport on Rails - How Do We Keep Fit At MarsBased</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d605.y35/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People coming from IT backgrounds mostly suffer from the same ailments as executives: back aches, migraine, circulation problems, eye dryness, stress. Luckily enough, we’ve got our own methods to fight these ailments back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Offices are evolving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last years we have seen some innovation in the offices. Companies are bringing in new hardware such as standing desks, ergonomical mouses &amp;amp; pointing devices or having rotational seats. Also, standing up every now and then to stretch your legs is now allowed and encouraged, contrary to the strictness of the 80s, mostly thanks to wireless communications and devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However healthier that might sound, these perks are not yet an established practice in Spanish companies yet, and they seem to be adopted only by start-ups and like-minded companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we can’t really tell you what to do to reduce the negative effects of sitting for too long, we will explain how we’re battling sedentarism at MarsBased. Of course, you can also follow some well-known tips like commuting to work on foot, answering phone calls while standing or even installing software that dims the screen’s brightness naturally to reduce eye dryness such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://justgetflux.com/&quot; title=&quot;Get F.lux&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;f.lux&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Working remotely&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a remote working company. Therefore, we get to move around our own homes/offices without anybody commenting on how often do we get up or how much do we slack off and/or procrastinate. Work gets done and deadlines are met regardless of our sitting position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We move around freely, sitting, standing or leaning wherever we want, changing position and seat multiple times a day. Having an own office also allows to customize it further than most offices, which are sometimes shared with other people or don’t allow much freedom to bring new appliances or hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sport within the company&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we wanted to encourage a healthier lifestyle within the company, last month we started the MarsBased Running Competition. The three Martians embarked in a running competition with different goals every fifteen days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.runkeeper.com&quot; title=&quot;Runkeeper&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Runkeeper&lt;/a&gt; as a tracking app, we track each other’s timings to compete. This way, we motivate each other to go jogging just for fun, and to avoid the shame of finishing in the last position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner doesn’t get rewarded and the loser doesn’t get punished or mocked. We do it for fun, and it actually is a good excuse to get adrenaline flowing before going into a concentration phase or burning all the calories ingested in &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; business lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post11.png&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased shoes&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased shoes&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-circle img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Not the best shoes for running, but gotta be corporate!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sport outside the company&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we were invited to take part in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupdodgeball.net/bcn.html&quot; title=&quot;Startup Dodgeball&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Dodgeball&lt;/a&gt;. We could not attend because we were putting the final touches to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bcn.cat/bcnstartupmap&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/a&gt;, so we decided to create our own event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of our first entries we told you about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://marsbased.com/blog/2013/11/07/start-up-circle-barcelona/&quot; title=&quot;Startup Circle in Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Circle&lt;/a&gt; we’re leading in Barcelona. Two weeks ago we decided to end the serious business-oriented meetings we were having and met for a football match and dinner. A good way to unwind from the daily grind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was well received within the community and we’re planning to do it again. We garnered ten members of this small community to play a game of indoors football that saw the birth of a very powerful interplanetary alliance between &lt;a href=&quot;http://mercurio-platform.com&quot; title=&quot;Mercurio Platform&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mercurio&lt;/a&gt; and MarsBased on the winning team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike rock bands, startups are not famous for their groupies (more for their lack thereof), at least in their early stages. Hence, no pictures were taken during the match!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re planning the next edition for the coming weeks, with our brothers from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dineyo.com&quot; title=&quot;Dineyo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dineyo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nektria.com&quot; title=&quot;Nektria&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nektria&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lemon8media.com/&quot; title=&quot;Lemon8 website&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Lemon8&lt;/a&gt; and the rest of the Startup Circle people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wanna join? Shoot an e-mail at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:hola@marsbased.com&quot; title=&quot;Mailto MarsBased&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;hola@marsbased.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 23:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/07/21/Sport-on-Rails</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/07/21/Sport-on-Rails</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Barcelona Startup Map (part 2)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d585.y35/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, 13th we attended the first Startup Grind Barcelona event held in the Mobile World Centre, right in the heart of Barcelona. As you might already know, we’re the technological partner of Startup Grind Barcelona (check out their &lt;a href=&quot;http://startupgrind.cat/&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona&#39;s website&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There, our CTO, Xavi, presented our latest project: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bcn.cat/bcnstartupmap&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/a&gt;. Here’s some impressions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Martians attend Startup Grind Barcelona&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 50 people witnessed the presentation of the map. First time entrepreneurs, long running freelancers, investors and a very diverse audience saw the possibilities of this webapp that connects the whole Barcelona Startup Ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did this tour of the app amidst other very interesting presentations on the event’s topic: entrepreneurship in sport. We presented after Oriol Serra (Nektria) and Guillermo Llibre (Gymforless).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startup Grind is always open to the community, and anybody is entitled to present their interesting projects to the entrepreneurial community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post10b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Xavier Redó presenting the Barcelona Startup Map&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Redó presenting the Barcelona Startup Map&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Xavier Redó, our CTO, presenting the Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;By the community, for the community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona Startup Map was first conceived as a tool to enable all the actors in the entrepreneurial ecosystem of Barcelona to interact with each other, by being able to find one another in a map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way, start-ups can find all the similar businesses in their area, and other services of they might need. For instance, let’s suppose our friends at Dineyo (red marker) are looking for investment in their own neighborhood. They can filter by the Investors typology and zoom in their area. There, they will find Nauta Capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s up to them to convince Nauta Capital to lend them some money! We can’t help any further with the map :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Some numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Barcelona Startup Map has been really well adopted since its release on the first week of June. It has had more than 50 signups in barely two weeks, which is almost five new registrations per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to increase participation, we’ve partnered with Startup Grind Barcelona to offer free entrance to the next SGBCN event to all companies registering before July, 15th! Register now and you’ll receive free tickets for the next Startup Grind on July, 15th with Marcos Alves (CEO @ Eltenedor.es).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Didn’t get yours? Send an email to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:hola@marsbased.com&quot; title=&quot;Our email address&quot;&gt;hola@marsbased.com&lt;/a&gt; to request your tickets or just to say hello :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/07/01/Barcelona-Startup-Map2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/07/01/Barcelona-Startup-Map2</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>