<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MarsBased</title>
    <description>MarsBased is an application development company in Barcelona, highly specialized in Ruby on Rails.</description>
    <link>http://www.marsbased.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.marsbased.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Our New Year&#39;s Resolutions for 2015</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d114.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2014 has been an amazing ride. It has seen us creating MarsBased, getting our first small projects, speaking at conferences, getting big projects, mentoring at IronHack, working for the Barcelona City Council, leading Startup Grind &amp;amp; Startup Circle, welcoming our first hires and many other amazing achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, we&amp;#39;re preparing a detailed review of 2014 for you all to enjoy and discover what&amp;#39;s been going on in the MarsBased spaceship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the 2014 post is being baked, we&amp;#39;ll share with you our new year resolutions for this promising 2015!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our first meeting of the year, everybody was asked what his resolutions for 2015 were, both personal and professional. Most of the resolutions are strongly related to our first months at MarsBased and/or our previous jobs, so we will be providing a little background to help you understand our resolutions better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not only help us bonding with each other, but it is also part of our new strategy of publishing more blog content and providing more transparency as a company (inspired in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://buffer.com&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Buffer&lt;/a&gt; guys, who are doing a terrific job at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bufferapp.com/transparency&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&#39;s Transparency policy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;helping new companies delving into corporate transparency&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In no particular order, here&amp;#39;s what the Martians pledged to achieve in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Xavier Redó - CTO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xavi started the year joining his previous company, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opscaling.com/&quot; title=&quot;GNuine&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GNuine&lt;/a&gt;, because we didn&amp;#39;t know we&amp;#39;d be able to recruit him so early. Our best guesstimates assumed we&amp;#39;d have to wait until the end of the year to have him working full-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past year has seen Xavi working hard to cope with all the projects we&amp;#39;ve gotten at MarsBased, therefore his resolutions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/xavi-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Xavier Redó&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Redó&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Xavier Redó&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CTO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Technologically speaking, I would like to be able to invest more time in exploring new technologies and frameworks to help us face the constant request of mobile apps.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Secondly, I would like to identify repeating patterns in our development processes in order to extract libraries we can reuse in the forthcoming projects and open source them when possible.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Leaving tech aside, I would like to participate more in events and conferences. I think I can add value in initiatives whose goal is to provide formation to new developers.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Actually, I can also provide interesting content online, so I will be contributing more to the MarsBased blog. We&#39;ve gathered some interesting results in 2014, and I would like to publish them and share them with our followers and the Rails community.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Finally, something I would like to improve is my time allocation skills. I am pretty accurate at guesstimating all the needed resources for each project, but so far I haven&#39;t included all these side-projects into my agenda. Here&#39;s to a 2015 for improvement!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Emilio Ríos - Developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emilio joined us barely a month and a half ago. But in our eyes, feels like he&amp;#39;s been with us for all the ride. He is, however, combining his internship at MarsBased with finishing his studies at La Salle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote right-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/emilio-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Emilio Ríos&quot; title=&quot;Emilio Ríos&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Emilio Ríos&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Developer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Since I have not been programming for long - at least not professionally - I would like to commit to improve my programming skills in 2015. Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://ejohn.org/blog/write-code-every-day/&quot; title=&quot;Write Code Every Day&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Resig&lt;/a&gt;, my new year resolution is to produce code every day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Now that my team-mates depend on me, I want to learn as much as possible to be helpful to them!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Javier Pérez - Developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javi joined MarsBased at the beginning of Q4, in early October. Having worked at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vass.es&quot; title=&quot;VASS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VASS&lt;/a&gt; together with Àlex, he transitioned from a full-time corporate J2EE consultant to an AngularJS/Rails developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same as Emilio, feels like he&amp;#39;s been forever with us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/javi-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Javier Pérez&quot; title=&quot;Javier Pérez&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Javier Pérez&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Developer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I would like to master Rails in the coming months so that I can be 100% autonomous in the projects I am assigned to. This way, I will also be able to explore new techniques &amp; trends on my own.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;By acquiring more knowledge on Rails, I will be able to spot recurring patterns that I can turn into libraries for our projects.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;On a personal side, and when I will be more autonomous, I would like to travel more. I want to enjoy this freedom of schedule we&#39;ve got and visit places I haven&#39;t been to!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Last, but not least, I would like to keep my condition of being single :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Àlex Rodríguez - CMO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started 2014 in San Francisco, having then recently quit my previous job at VASS, where I worked with Javi - actually, we were in the same project, sitting next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some weeks wandering around the city-cradle of entrepreneurship, I returned to Barcelona and got the Barcelona Startup Map project. That gave us the opportunity of employing me full time at the end of Q1, despite the fact that we were bootstrapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are my resolutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote right-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/alex-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Àlex Rodríguez&quot; title=&quot;Àlex Rodríguez&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Àlex Rodríguez&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CMO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;2014 was a year of working hard to meet all the deadlines &amp; cover all the areas of creating a company. I balanced my area&#39;s tasks (sales/marketing) with all sorts of other operational tasks to keep the development team focused.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This year I want to work smarter by focusing on my own areas (sales/marketing), while helping others improve in theirs.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Also, in terms of pushing my marketing skills to the next level, I want to learn graphic edition as well as improve my writing skills, publishing blog entries more often.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In terms of achievements, I would like to land a couple of big projects this year (if possible, from abroad). Also, I will be devoting more time to our presence in events, besides strengthening our relationship with Startup Grind &amp; Startup Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Jordi Vendrell - COO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordi is the third founding member at MarsBased. However, due to his duties as a Technical Director at Green Data and having a child last year, he couldn&amp;#39;t join MarsBased until now. He&amp;#39;s joining full-time on February, 9th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year he spent it balancing his position at Green Data, some hours during the weekends for MarsBased and his condition of first-time father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/jordi-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jordi Vendrell&quot; title=&quot;Jordi Vendrell&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Jordi Vendrell&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;COO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I only ask that on 2015 I will be able to combine professional and personal life better: spend more time with my family, get fit and keep doing a great job.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;As for MarsBased, I would like to produce a new version of our corporate website that stands up to our status nowadays. It has to be a kick-ass website! Also, I&#39;m looking forward to being more involved in the operative work of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;... and you? What are your resolutions for this year? Share them in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 07:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/01/20/Our-New-Years-Resolutions-For-20154</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/01/20/Our-New-Years-Resolutions-For-20154</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our First Christmas Dinner</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d87.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s been two months since our last status update, and we wanted to let you know we&amp;#39;re far from dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a fledging progression that has seen us completing our first projects after the summer, a couple of new big challenges have popped up. All these projects have kept us swamped with work, but they are also a reason to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, 2014 has brought many good achievements and landmarks for our company. But none of them can compare to celebrating our first Christmas dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A year in review&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MarsBased spaceship has been working at full capacity to complete the ongoing projects we have had thus far, having barely no time to update the blog. While we can&amp;#39;t wait to tell you everything we are undergoing at the moment, we also need to meet the deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s review the steps we have taken to reach this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MarsBased as a company was founded in March this year, after I came back from San Francisco. Signing all the required documentation to create the company was both relieving and challenging, and definitely has changed our lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing some minor projects, we got the opportunity of working for Barcelona Activa, in the creation of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bcn.cat/bcnstartupMap&quot; title=&quot;BCN Startup Map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/a&gt;. This project gave us enough propulsion (both economically and visiblity-wise) to start working on other projects. Also, through this project we were contacted by other companies who wanted to hire our services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the summer we landed the project of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eureka-startups.com&quot; title=&quot;Eureka Startups&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Eureka Startups Experts&lt;/a&gt; (still in progress), and a couple of other projects, that allowed both Xavi and I to go full time for the company. As a result of that, we boosted our production capacity, which means we could take on more &amp;amp; bigger projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working full-time, we could also start going to events, thus increasing our visibility in the scene. We participated in numerous events, organizing meetings with the Startup Circle, collaborating with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupgrind.cat&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Grind&lt;/a&gt;, mentoring at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ironhack.com&quot; title=&quot;IronHack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IronHack&lt;/a&gt;, giving speeches at congresses, attending &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.baruco.org&quot; title=&quot;Baruco&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Baruco&lt;/a&gt;, and meeting fantastic people everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was in September-October that we landed a couple of big projects from abroad (details to be disclosed soon!). These two projects have given us enough stability to hire &lt;a href=&quot;http://marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/18/The-MarsBased-Team-Grows-Bigger-The-Abduction/&quot; title=&quot;Our blog post of our first hire&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Javi&lt;/a&gt; to increase our development capacity again. Soon thereafter, we got the opportunity of welcoming our first intern &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MarsBased/status/538760313836158976&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased welcomes Emilio Rios&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Emilio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A Martian Christmas dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Wednesday we got together and spent a whole evening celebrating the first MarsBased Christmas dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a remote working company, this kind of get-togethers are essential to help bonding with the team at a personal level. They also increase happiness in the company and provide a good way to talk about stuff that&amp;#39;s normally not covered in the corporate chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evening started at &lt;a href=&quot;https://foursquare.com/v/la-cerveseria-clandestina/50447f7de4b072dc97475858&quot; title=&quot;La Cervecería Clanestina&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cervecería Clandestina&lt;/a&gt; to taste a selection of the finest beers. Barcelona is not famous for its craft beer yet, but it&amp;#39;s a growing trend that is getting very popular in the last years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post15a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased team at Cervecería Clandestina&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased team at Cervecería Clandestina&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Beer makes people more proficient in foreign languages such as Martian!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dinner took place in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://foursquare.com/v/lomb%C3%BA/4c0ab162009a0f475fe1e9bf&quot;title=&quot;Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Restaurant L&amp;#39;Ombú&lt;/a&gt;. A very cozy restaurant hidden between the Gracia and Horta districts in Barcelona. A well-kept secret for fusion cuisine mixing tradicional Catalan recipes with the latest trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post15c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Enjoying tasty Earth food at Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; title=&quot;Enjoying tasty Earth food at Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Enjoying tasty Earth food at Restaurant L&amp;#39;Ombú.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post15d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased team at Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased team at Restaurant L&#39;Ombú&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;The MarsBased team at Restaurant L&amp;#39;Ombú.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the restaurant we spent hours talking about the company and its future, and we toasted to our success in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evening came to a close at the famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://foursquare.com/v/elephanta/4b510121f964a5201a3d27e3&quot; title=&quot;L&#39;Elephanta&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;L&amp;#39;Elephanta&lt;/a&gt;, one of the best gin&amp;amp;tonic places in Barcelona. Conversation drifted to off-topic mode and provided an excellent ending to a lovely evening out enjoying a good share of teambuilding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post15e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased team at L&#39;Elephanta&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased team at L&#39;Elephanta&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Martian advise: Don&amp;#39;t drink &amp;amp; drive spaceships.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are ecstatic to have been able to celebrate such a landmark in our career and looking forward to kicking off 2015 stronger than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy &lt;code&gt;I18n.translate :local_winter_celebration&lt;/code&gt; everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2014 07:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/12/23/Our-First-Christmas-Dinner</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/12/23/Our-First-Christmas-Dinner</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dealing With Your First Hire in a Distributed Team</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d30.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last blog entry we described our first day with our new hire, Javi. Two weeks in, and the whole team has felt the boost of having a new employee at MarsBased: the company is producing more, he&amp;#39;s learning while having fun, and so are we.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a new employee brings in a whole set of risks that need to be adressed when running your own company. One of them is the integration in the team, and this is what this entry is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re talking about our first employee here. &lt;i&gt;Serious business&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having read a lot of literature on how to deal with this situation, we found these tips worth sharing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Day to day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When introducing a new hire to your company, you need to make sure he feels integrated as soon as possible, specially in small companies. And even more so if he/she is your very first hire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most valuable piece of advice here is &lt;i&gt;work naturally&lt;/i&gt;. 37Signals&amp;#39; book &lt;a href=&quot;http://37signals.com/remote/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Remote: No Office Required&quot;&gt;Remote: No Office Required&lt;/a&gt; strongly advises companies to continue working like they did before the employee was hired. Changing your behaviour will look like unnatural and will create awkward situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be yourselves while making him part of team decisions, not leaving him out of meetings, and showing him everything is there to learn. Obviously, you&amp;#39;ll be spending some time teaching him all that stuff, but consider this as an investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, terms like &amp;quot;family&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; should be avoided. After all, this is a business relationship. Experts tend to favour the usage of expressions such as &amp;quot;we&amp;#39;re a team&amp;quot;, instead. Or else, no mentioning of this at all. &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.hbr.org/2014/06/your-company-is-not-a-family/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Your Business Is Not A Family&quot;&gt;This blog post&lt;/a&gt; explains the situation very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line here is: show, don&amp;#39;t tell. Your actions will be more valuable than your words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Roles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distributed teams meet seldom. In these companies, the limits of your duties and/or responsibilities are sometimes unclear. Specially if the introduction to the company isn&amp;#39;t done right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue can be avoided by introducing the team accordingly, and telling the new hire clearly what you expect from him or her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, when hiring a new programmer, do not send him into coding without explaining what&amp;#39;s your coding style, which metodologies do you use, whether you do pair programming or not, which technologies do you expect him to know, the frequency of your commits, what additional tasks will he have to handle (devops, code refactoring, QA, performance tests, etc.) and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these situations, it is better to tell them what they are expected to do according to their role, but that they set the limits to their involvement with the company. That is: programmers deal with the development of the apps, but they have the option of getting involved with social media, writing in the blog, participating in the sales processes, improving internal organizational processes, preparing workshops for events, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides that, in small teams, the figure of the leader - bosses who work by your side - is enforced, instead of the classical boss enclosed in his own office. An almost-flat hierarchy helps easing this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post14.png&quot; alt=&quot;Remote: No office required&quot; title=&quot;Remote: No office required&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://37signals.com/remote/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Remote: No Office Required&quot;&gt;Remote: No Office Required&lt;/a&gt; is one of our favourite books and a mandatory read for distributed teams.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Communication is key&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending half a day listing all the communication tools you use as a team, and how to use them, is never a waste of time. On the contrary: set the rules now, and forget about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://basecamp.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Basecamp&quot;&gt;Basecamp&lt;/a&gt; for internal discussion that needs to be recorded. Then we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://slack.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Slack&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt; for in-real-time communication and having the water-cooler effect of always having someone to talk to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hardly ever email each other save for communications with third parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it is very important to present all the tools to the new hire, as well as the frequency of use and some rules that need to be met to ensure a fluid &amp;amp; correct communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Get-togethers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, get-togethers, for work or leisure, are necessary in all remote working companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a team that never sees each other&amp;#39;s faces save for videocalls. As hard as they might try, there&amp;#39;s a great chance they will not bond as much as a normal company due to the lack of physical connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In distributed teams, not everybody lives in the same city. In some cases, you might even have an employee in the other side of the globe, that might probably feel a little left out if not dealt with properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get-togethers help bridging that gap. They create a sense of bonding that should be enforced regularly, depending on the maturity and budget of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, get-togethers for working will also boost productivity for a day. Instead of everyone working separately, try getting the team together in the same room for a day. This will boost creativity and create an exciting vibe to get more stuff done before the session ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, get-togethers on the new employee&amp;#39;s first day are also critical to help easing the introduction to the rest of the crew. He or she will want to meet the bosses &amp;amp; coworkers on the first day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the company side, that shows appreciation and interest in the new employee. Not only will this help him/her gelling in with the rest of the crew, but they can all get to know one another in a more natural way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your company a distributed team as well? Feel free to share your tips and experiences with us in the comments below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/25/Dealing-With-Your-First-Hire-In-A-Distributed-Team</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/25/Dealing-With-Your-First-Hire-In-A-Distributed-Team</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The MarsBased Team Grows Bigger: The Abduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d23.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, October 7th will be a date to remember for all the Martians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last few months we have been swamped with work. Far from being a quiet and relaxed summer, the MarsBased flagship has been advancing at cruise speed. And to face the coming months, we hired a new developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s what we did in our first day with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;In the last chapter of The MarsBased Diaries...&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the summer we have been working non-stop to make MarsBased grow bigger, looking for larger projects that would allow an organic and sustainable growth of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out, one of the first contacts we ever made as MarsBased reached out and hired us for a very ambitious project we hope to disclose very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is big. So big that &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/xavier_redo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Redó Twitter handle&quot;&gt;Xavi&lt;/a&gt;, our CTO, could not complete it on his own in the given dates. So we hired a new Martian called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/_iamjavi_&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Javi&#39;s Twitter handle&quot;&gt;Javier Pérez&lt;/a&gt;, who has an extensive background in IT consulting and webapps development. Plus he&amp;#39;s got a beard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Abduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we&amp;#39;re a remote working company, we do not have a physical office. We always meet our clients at their offices and seldom hold any get-togethers by now. So we went out for some coworking at one of the best venues in town: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.start2bee.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Start2bee coworking space&quot;&gt;Start2bee&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javi is our first hire at MarsBased, so we made sure we gave him the best possible welcoming to the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He showed up with his new &amp;amp; shiny Macbook Pro and after having read the Martian Playbook, prepared for a day-long session of initiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post13a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MarsBased abduction&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased abduction&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;MarsBased corporate presentation to commence the abduction!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session kicked off with a formal presentation of the company: who we are, what are our working methods and what do we offer as a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then reviewed the MarsBased Playbook to emphasize the importance of communication and mutual understanding in distributed teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the first half of the coworking session ended with a review of the company history, project by project, to help understand our progress as a company up until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch, we started rolling: Xavi and Javi teamed up to start pair-programming while the rest of the team worked on project definition and estimations for potential clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Immediate future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our biggest challenge is to integrate Javi into the MarsBased culture &amp;amp; working methods as soon and natural as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His challenge is to help us achieve the goals we&amp;#39;ve set, that we couldn&amp;#39;t achieve without him, while bringing a whole lot of expertise in Javascript to our tech stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for that, he (also) got a corporate coffee mug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post13c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MarsBased coffee mug&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased coffee mug&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;MarsBased coffee mug with our new logo!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome aboard, Javi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: Xavi and Javi will be pair-programming during the next weeks at Start2bee a couple of days a week. Drop by to say hello, if you&amp;#39;re around!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/18/The-MarsBased-Team-Grows-Bigger-The-Abduction</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/10/18/The-MarsBased-Team-Grows-Bigger-The-Abduction</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Martians Conquer the IronHack</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d636.y35/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we created MarsBased, we decided to be a social, outgoing and media-friendly company. We also wanted to help the community, to pay back what the community had helped us in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early stages of a company, this is however something hard to achieve. The first priorities should be creating the company, establishing an organized accounting culture and sales, and developing your product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the cash comes in, and stabilizes the company, you can take some time to contribute back to the community. While it&amp;#39;s not mandatory, it clearly helps developing a friendly attitude as a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, we have been helping newcomers in the Ruby community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Enter the IronHack&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we created the company, we compiled a list of the leading Ruby development shops we wanted to meet and learn from. We threw in a bunch of names such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://thoughtbot.com/&quot; title=&quot;Thoughbot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thoughtbot&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codegram.com/&quot; title=&quot;Codegram&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Codegram&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://plataformatec.com.br/&quot; title=&quot;Plataformatec&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Plataformatec&lt;/a&gt; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last December, when I embarked in &lt;a href=&quot;http://startupoddity.ghost.io/meeting-san-francisco/&quot; title=&quot;Startup Oddity Blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;my trip to San Francisco&lt;/a&gt;, I reached out to the all of them and got a fair share of replies, hence meeting the guys from &lt;a href=&quot;http://thoughtbot.com/&quot; title=&quot;Thoughbot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thoughtbot&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://monterail.com/&quot; title=&quot;Monterail&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Monterail&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://prorubyteam.com/&quot; title=&quot;ProRuby&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ProRuby&lt;/a&gt;, just to name a few. All of them vowed to help us like they had been once helped, and gave us very useful pieces of advice. It was, indeed, a very promising start!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also added to the list some developer bootcamps, completely ignoring the fact that most of them work exclusively with top-class companies and developers. However, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ironhack.com/&quot; title=&quot;IronHack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IronHack&lt;/a&gt; replied back nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Time Flies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some months of chatting back and forth, I received an email from them asking for collaborators for their summer edition in Barcelona. We were invited to know them in person, at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mob-barcelona.com/&quot; title=&quot;Makers of Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MOB&lt;/a&gt;, and introduced to their team assistants and guest teachers: top Ruby and Javascript developers, working for Xing, Spotify and other leading companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IronHack bootcamp runs for two months with full dedication to learning coding: Rails, AngularJS, Javascript and what it takes to create state-of-the-art webapps. After their daily dose of programming, the session is completed with talks regarding different subjects: branding, accounting, marketing and all kinds of useful stuff. We were asked to provide two talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;First Talk: Create your Company NOW&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was honoured to give the first talk of the current edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I know that most people there are passionate about web applications and will end their IronHack program creating an app (because it&amp;#39;s their final project), I thought it would be useful to motivate them. What if they didn&amp;#39;t only program that app for IronHack? What if they could create a startup around it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Prezi to create a motivational presentation using their fantastic Space template (fits perfectly with our Martian imagery) and rallied the troops to go out and create their startup right NOW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post12a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Àlex presenting at IronHack&quot; title=&quot;Àlex presenting at IronHack&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Warning! The presentation contains profanity!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://prezi.com/ttqvo8ssl6ew/create-your-company-from-out-of-this-world/&quot; title=&quot;Prepare your business to sky-rocket&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Get the presentation here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Second Talk: Bulding Large Webapps That Are Easy to Maintain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later, Xavi provided a largely comprehensive talk on how to build large web applications to be easily maintainable. While the presentation dealt mostly with Rails best practices, it contained a fair share of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=lulz&amp;defid=2539255&quot; title=&quot;Definition of lulz&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lulz&lt;/a&gt;. At MarsBased we enforce the use of meme-driven presentations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post12b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Xavi presenting at IronHack&quot; title=&quot;Xavi presenting at IronHack&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Meme-driven technical presentation!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/12625879/MarsBased/Ironhack%20presentation.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Bulding Large Webapps That Are Easy to Maintain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Get the presentation here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback we received was so good that we were invited to an afterwork event on the rooftop of Betahaus, where we talked everything: from loving or hating TDD, to everyone&amp;#39;s future plans or why Barcelona is the best city in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We definitely connected with the IronHack community and want to get more involved in the coming editions to make more people love coding and Ruby on Rails. So far, we can say we will be mentoring at the next edition of IronHack in Barcelona!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you meet us at IronHack? We would appreciate if you left some feedback in the comments section!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love from Mars.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2014 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/08/22/The-Martians-conquer-the-IronHack</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/08/22/The-Martians-conquer-the-IronHack</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sport on Rails - How Do We Keep Fit At MarsBased</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d605.y35/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People coming from IT backgrounds mostly suffer from the same ailments as executives: back aches, migraine, circulation problems, eye dryness, stress. Luckily enough, we’ve got our own methods to fight these ailments back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Offices are evolving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last years we have seen some innovation in the offices. Companies are bringing in new hardware such as standing desks, ergonomical mouses &amp;amp; pointing devices or having rotational seats. Also, standing up every now and then to stretch your legs is now allowed and encouraged, contrary to the strictness of the 80s, mostly thanks to wireless communications and devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However healthier that might sound, these perks are not yet an established practice in Spanish companies yet, and they seem to be adopted only by start-ups and like-minded companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we can’t really tell you what to do to reduce the negative effects of sitting for too long, we will explain how we’re battling sedentarism at MarsBased. Of course, you can also follow some well-known tips like commuting to work on foot, answering phone calls while standing or even installing software that dims the screen’s brightness naturally to reduce eye dryness such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://justgetflux.com/&quot; title=&quot;Get F.lux&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;f.lux&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Working remotely&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a remote working company. Therefore, we get to move around our own homes/offices without anybody commenting on how often do we get up or how much do we slack off and/or procrastinate. Work gets done and deadlines are met regardless of our sitting position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We move around freely, sitting, standing or leaning wherever we want, changing position and seat multiple times a day. Having an own office also allows to customize it further than most offices, which are sometimes shared with other people or don’t allow much freedom to bring new appliances or hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sport within the company&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we wanted to encourage a healthier lifestyle within the company, last month we started the MarsBased Running Competition. The three Martians embarked in a running competition with different goals every fifteen days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.runkeeper.com&quot; title=&quot;Runkeeper&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Runkeeper&lt;/a&gt; as a tracking app, we track each other’s timings to compete. This way, we motivate each other to go jogging just for fun, and to avoid the shame of finishing in the last position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner doesn’t get rewarded and the loser doesn’t get punished or mocked. We do it for fun, and it actually is a good excuse to get adrenaline flowing before going into a concentration phase or burning all the calories ingested in &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; business lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post11.png&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased shoes&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased shoes&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-circle img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Not the best shoes for running, but gotta be corporate!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sport outside the company&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we were invited to take part in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupdodgeball.net/bcn.html&quot; title=&quot;Startup Dodgeball&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Dodgeball&lt;/a&gt;. We could not attend because we were putting the final touches to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bcn.cat/bcnstartupmap&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/a&gt;, so we decided to create our own event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of our first entries we told you about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://marsbased.com/blog/2013/11/07/start-up-circle-barcelona/&quot; title=&quot;Startup Circle in Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Circle&lt;/a&gt; we’re leading in Barcelona. Two weeks ago we decided to end the serious business-oriented meetings we were having and met for a football match and dinner. A good way to unwind from the daily grind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was well received within the community and we’re planning to do it again. We garnered ten members of this small community to play a game of indoors football that saw the birth of a very powerful interplanetary alliance between &lt;a href=&quot;http://mercurio-platform.com&quot; title=&quot;Mercurio Platform&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mercurio&lt;/a&gt; and MarsBased on the winning team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike rock bands, startups are not famous for their groupies (more for their lack thereof), at least in their early stages. Hence, no pictures were taken during the match!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re planning the next edition for the coming weeks, with our brothers from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dineyo.com&quot; title=&quot;Dineyo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dineyo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nektria.com&quot; title=&quot;Nektria&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nektria&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lemon8media.com/&quot; title=&quot;Lemon8 website&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Lemon8&lt;/a&gt; and the rest of the Startup Circle people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wanna join? Shoot an e-mail at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:hola@marsbased.com&quot; title=&quot;Mailto MarsBased&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;hola@marsbased.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 14:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/07/21/Sport-on-Rails</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/07/21/Sport-on-Rails</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Barcelona Startup Map (part 2)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d585.y35/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, 13th we attended the first Startup Grind Barcelona event held in the Mobile World Centre, right in the heart of Barcelona. As you might already know, we’re the technological partner of Startup Grind Barcelona (check out their &lt;a href=&quot;http://startupgrind.cat/&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona&#39;s website&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There, our CTO, Xavi, presented our latest project: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bcn.cat/bcnstartupmap&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/a&gt;. Here’s some impressions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Martians attend Startup Grind Barcelona&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 50 people witnessed the presentation of the map. First time entrepreneurs, long running freelancers, investors and a very diverse audience saw the possibilities of this webapp that connects the whole Barcelona Startup Ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did this tour of the app amidst other very interesting presentations on the event’s topic: entrepreneurship in sport. We presented after Oriol Serra (Nektria) and Guillermo Llibre (Gymforless).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startup Grind is always open to the community, and anybody is entitled to present their interesting projects to the entrepreneurial community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post10b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Xavier Redó presenting the Barcelona Startup Map&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Redó presenting the Barcelona Startup Map&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Xavier Redó, our CTO, presenting the Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;By the community, for the community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona Startup Map was first conceived as a tool to enable all the actors in the entrepreneurial ecosystem of Barcelona to interact with each other, by being able to find one another in a map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way, start-ups can find all the similar businesses in their area, and other services of they might need. For instance, let’s suppose our friends at Dineyo (red marker) are looking for investment in their own neighborhood. They can filter by the Investors typology and zoom in their area. There, they will find Nauta Capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s up to them to convince Nauta Capital to lend them some money! We can’t help any further with the map :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Some numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Barcelona Startup Map has been really well adopted since its release on the first week of June. It has had more than 50 signups in barely two weeks, which is almost five new registrations per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to increase participation, we’ve partnered with Startup Grind Barcelona to offer free entrance to the next SGBCN event to all companies registering before July, 15th! Register now and you’ll receive free tickets for the next Startup Grind on July, 15th with Marcos Alves (CEO @ Eltenedor.es).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Didn’t get yours? Send an email to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:hola@marsbased.com&quot; title=&quot;Our email address&quot;&gt;hola@marsbased.com&lt;/a&gt; to request your tickets or just to say hello :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 03:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/07/01/Barcelona-Startup-Map2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/07/01/Barcelona-Startup-Map2</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Barcelona Startup Map (part 1)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d564.y35/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are very happy to announce that two days ago we launched our biggest project to date. Together with the Barcelona City Hall and Barcelona Activa - the executive tool of the Economic Development policies of the Barcelona City Council - we launched &lt;a href=&quot;http://bcn.cat/bcnstartupmap&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona Startup Map&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know more about the app? Keep reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;We support the Barcelona local scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post9a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Barcelona Startup Map, The entrepreneurial ecosystem of Barcelona&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona Startup Map is a web application that displays the current state of the Barcelona entrepreneurial ecosystem in a map. Through Barcelona Startup Map, you will be able to find, geolocate and add start-ups, investors, accelerators/incubators, talent centers and venues providing services to entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona Startup Map, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spainstartupmap.com/&quot; title=&quot;SpainStartupMap&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SpainStartupMap&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://techbritain.com/&quot; title=&quot;TechBritain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TechBritain&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mappedinisrael.com/&quot; title=&quot;MappedInIsrael&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MappedInIsrael&lt;/a&gt; and similar initiatives, provides a quick overview of the resources available to entrepreneurs in a certain area or city. Simply, if investors want to know whether the Barcelona start-up scene is solid enough, they will load Barcelona Startup Map to get the picture. To help the visitor understand the mapped data quicker and further, we are adding infographics as more data is brought into the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, the platform is only available to companies and individuals based in Barcelona. If the platform is well received, though, it will evolve to incorporate all the Metropolitan Area surrounding Barcelona or even a larger area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Presentation at BizBarcelona&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post9b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; class=&quot;img-right img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona Startup Map was made publicly available during the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizbarcelona.com/&quot; title=&quot;BizBarcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BizBarcelona&lt;/a&gt;. An institutional presentation speech was made by Sònia Recasens (Deputy Mayor of Barcelona) stating the good health of the entrepreneurial scene in Barcelona. Itziar Blasco (head of new incubation models at Barcelona Activa) did shortly afterwards a quick demo of the app, showing all its possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because both &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-2162027/Microsofts-Surface-tablet-crashes-stage--repeat-Bill-Gates-Windows-98-blue-screen-death-moment.html&quot; title=&quot;Microsoft FAIL&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vzDDO3Xb_QU&quot; title=&quot;Apple FAIL&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Apple&lt;/a&gt; had major FAIL moments during the presentations of their products, we prepared for the worst. However, the app behaved as expected and the presentation was therefore successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post9c.png&quot; alt=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Map&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Itziar Blasco (head of new incubation models at Barcelona Activa), doing a demo of the app&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the demo, our co-founder Àlex Rodríguez directed a round table discussing the Barcelona entrepreneurial ecosystem. The guests were chosen to have one person representing each resource type: Gloria Molins (CEO @ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trip4real.com/&quot; title=&quot;Trip4Real&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Trip4Real&lt;/a&gt;), Daniel Sánchez (Founder @ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nautacapital.com/&quot; title=&quot;NautaCapital&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NautaCapital&lt;/a&gt;), Juan Pérez (Director at &lt;a href=&quot;http://technovabarcelona.org&quot; title=&quot;Innovator Park La Salle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Innovator Park La Salle&lt;/a&gt;), Iolanda Triviño (CEO @ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.valkiriahubspace.com&quot; title=&quot;Valkiria Hub Space&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Valkiria Hub Space&lt;/a&gt;) and Andrés Mansó (CEO @ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.incubio.com&quot; title=&quot;Incubio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Incubio&lt;/a&gt;). Each one shared in turns their opinion on the evolution of their sector in the last years, the current state and a prediction of where is the situation going. All of them had a common vision: the city had been nurturing its entrepreneurial tissue for some years, and is now ready for something big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last years, Barcelona has been building up a very competitive entrepreneurial ecosystem. The number of new start-ups, acceleration and incubation programs, investors and coworking spaces, has grown very rapidly. All these actors are nowadays teaming up to create innovative, solid and disrupting projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Next steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work here is not over. This is just the beginning of our collaboration with the Barcelona start-up scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about the map, such as the technical details or what did we take from this project, stay tuned. We are currently preparing a second part to this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, we will keep making apps out of this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love from Mars!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/06/09/Barcelona-Startup-Map1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/06/09/Barcelona-Startup-Map1</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Celebrating the first Martian year</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d495.y35/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week has been definitely a turning point in the life of MarsBased. Coincidentally, we also celebrated our first MarsBased birthday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s been truly memorable: not only did we enjoy a delicious cake commemorating the first year of the Martian family, but we sealed the biggest project to date for MarsBased, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post8a.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Mars Cake&quot; title=&quot;The Mars Cake&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;The countdown on the cake is over, time to take-off&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of our first year, we spend it building our portfolio and tools such as Cookin.me, which we are releasing as open source in an alpha phase. The last few months, however, we devoted our time to work for other companies building apps and killer websites for them. Our customers are happy, and so are we.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one year we have sealed projects abroad, attended some big events and, as MarsBased completed some important goals, we&amp;#39;ve learned and had fun along the way. On a funnier side, we&amp;#39;ve received job applications before we had any projects, we got the Nigerian prince scam, and two companies even tried to acquire MarsBased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To celebrate this first anniversary, we want to share some of our best moments with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Learn by doing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the best decision we have adopted at MarsBased was to always keep busy. Without a doubt, we learn by doing. In just one year we&amp;#39;ve learnt more than what we would have learnt by reading expensive publications or in an MBA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also refined our company culture by applying our values in our daily routine. We like to make better stuff by simplifying it, so we simplified our communication workflows and tool belt. Every week we devote some time to improve our routines and working methods to increase our productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased we also like to adopt new technologies. Our latest adoptions have been &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot; title=&quot;Jekyll&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://coffeescript.org/&quot; title=&quot;Coffeescript&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Coffeescript&lt;/a&gt; for our developments. We&amp;#39;ve as well cut down on communication channels by adopting &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.com/&quot; title=&quot;Slack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Community giveback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MarsBased are fully committed to contribute to the entrepreneurial scene that saw us grow. More than half a year ago we created the start-up circle with some friends, and now has grown to over 7 start-ups and more than 15 participants. Sooner rather than later we will build a website for the circle where you&amp;#39;ll be able to find more information about us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MarsBased has also lately become the technological partner of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupgrind.cat&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Grind Barcelona&lt;/a&gt;, for which we are building a killer website at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupgrind.cat&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.startupgrind.cat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these months, we&amp;#39;ve gotten to know amazing companies such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thesocialcoin.org/&quot; title=&quot;The Social Coin&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Social Coin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nektria.com/&quot; title=&quot;Nektria&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nektria&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thoughtbot.com/&quot; title=&quot;Thoughtbot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thoughtbot&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://monterail.com/&quot; title=&quot;Monterail&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Monterail&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://prorubyteam.com/&quot; title=&quot;ProRuby&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ProRuby&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docsend.com/&quot; title=&quot;DocSend&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DocSend&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.typeform.com/&quot; title=&quot;TypeForm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TypeForm&lt;/a&gt;, etc. As we&amp;#39;re in this together, we&amp;#39;ve always sought to help one another. Think global, act local.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;And now, onto the second year!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where are we now? As we speak, we&amp;#39;re probably in three different geographical points in Catalonia. That&amp;#39;s how we work: we might not necessarily know where the others are, but we know we&amp;#39;re always there. Work-wise, however, we are 100% sure of where we stand: we&amp;#39;re set to work on our biggest project to date, while putting the final touches to our most recent projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few months, we have become a more mature company with clear roles &amp;amp; responsibilities. We have transitioned from being a product company to selling our services and our expertise. Our focus is now set on understanding the customer&amp;#39;s needs and making our vision converge with theirs to get to the heart of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our plan for the year ahead is to work with more and more diverse customers. Deliver to each and every one of them an entirely breathtaking product that we will later break down in our blog, describing the process we&amp;#39;ve been through from the very inception to its final delivery. And what&amp;#39;s more: we want to keep having fun while working, because it&amp;#39;s intrinsically rooted in the MarsBased DNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we want our customers to enjoy the ride with us. We grow, if they grow. We learn, if they learn. And we&amp;#39;re satisfied, if they are too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to make consultancy simple, fun, and down-to-earth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2014 07:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/03/30/Celebrating-the-first-Martian-year</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/03/30/Celebrating-the-first-Martian-year</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We make the right app for you (part 2)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d489.y35/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: long (and nerdy) post ahead.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our last entry we wrote about MarsBased&amp;#39;s principles when working for other companies, because we have recently been hired to develop our first projects. In this entry, we are breaking down our tool belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Front-end Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MarsBased stands for innovation by using state-of-the-art technologies. HTML5, CSS3 and both Javascript and front-end frameworks - such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/&quot; title=&quot;Bootstrap&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://angularjs.org/&quot; title=&quot;AngularJS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt; - allow us to deliver responsive and highly dynamic websites with an unparalleled User Experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post6.png&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased Tech Stack&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased Tech Stack&quot; class=&quot;img-right img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter Bootstrap is a front-end framework created to design websites faster and easier. Its last version adopts a &amp;quot;mobile first&amp;quot; philosophy providing tools to create responsive sites. Nowadays, every competitive website needs to be responsive, due to the rise of mobile traffic in multiple-sized screens or the latest Google algorithm changes, focusing on mobile experience (Google Hummingbird explained &lt;a href=&quot;http://venturebeat.com/2013/10/02/things-not-strings-how-googles-new-hummingbird-algorithm-sets-the-stage-for-the-future-of-mobile-search/&quot; title=&quot;Google Hummingbird&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another technology we use is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lesscss.org/&quot; title=&quot;LESS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LESS&lt;/a&gt;. As a dynamic stylesheet language, LESS introduces variables, functions and operators in your stylesheets and preprocesses them. By doing that, designers can actually focus on designing, without having to write long, repetitive and tedious CSS stylesheets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the Javascript side, we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://angularjs.org/&quot; title=&quot;AngularJS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt;. AngularJS is a Javascript framework designed to build single-page web applications as if they were native by removing all the Javascript boilerplate. By doing that, AngularJS gives the browser the power it needs to materialize our ideas into something real using richer client-side interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent addition to the MarsBased tech stack has been &lt;a href=&quot;http://coffeescript.org/&quot; title=&quot;Coffeescript&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Coffeescript&lt;/a&gt;. Coffeescript allows rewriting Javascript code with simplicity and elegance. After some research and testing, we integrated both Coffeescript and AngularJS with Cookin.me and fell in love with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Server Side Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are Rubyists! We love its simplicity, elegance and cleanliness. And while we believe that methodologies are language-agnostic, &lt;a title=&quot;Ruby&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ruby-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Ruby&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a title=&quot;Ruby on Rails&quot; href=&quot;http://rubyonrails.org/&quot;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt; help us follow Agile Development practices. That&amp;#39;s the reason why we have chosen tools that let us move quickly through each development stage: building, integrating, testing &amp;amp; releasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased we take testing &lt;em&gt;very seriously&lt;/em&gt;. We know that our clients might require changes over time, and might want to introduce improvements to their apps. The only way we can ensure delivering these changes without breaking the entire codebase of the project is through testing. Test, test, test and then some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have adopted two popular ruby frameworks for our testing needs. With &lt;a title=&quot;RSpec&quot; href=&quot;http://rspec.info&quot;&gt;RSpec&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a title=&quot;Capybara&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/jnicklas/capybara&quot;&gt;Capybara&lt;/a&gt; we feel very comfortable applying a test driven development approach from unit testing to building acceptance tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more specific projects, we have a flexible tool belt. According to every project&amp;#39;s needs, we&amp;#39;ve got a broad set of technologies at hand to give our clients exactly what they need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;ElasticSearch&quot; href=&quot;http://www.elasticsearch.org&quot;&gt;ElasticSearch&lt;/a&gt;: For indexing and searching through our client data without affecting performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Sidekiq&quot; href=&quot;http://sidekiq.org&quot;&gt;Sidekiq&lt;/a&gt;: Handy when there&amp;#39;s a lot of background processing jobs - like image and video transformations, web crawling or big data processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Memcached&quot; href=&quot;http://memcached.org&quot;&gt;Memcached&lt;/a&gt;: Caches almost every little part of a web application to achieve blazing fast responses, thus keeping response times low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Redis&quot; href=&quot;http://redis.io&quot;&gt;Redis&lt;/a&gt;: Manages big amounts of volatile data faster than any relational database can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Deployment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small teams need to automate and or delegate processes to manage recurrent tasks. This is why we use &lt;a title=&quot;Chef&quot; href=&quot;http://www.getchef.com/&quot;&gt;Chef&lt;/a&gt;: to automatically provision our servers. Automation spares us from having to log into our servers (this is so last century&amp;#39;s!) and guarantees that no human errors will happen during server installations. All the time we save by automating, we can use it in polishing their apps even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of our background using Chef, we have a custom set of configurations (called &lt;em&gt;cookbooks&lt;/em&gt; in Chef jargon) that cover all the possible scenarios we could ever need. We don&amp;#39;t need to reinvent the wheel for every project. We can set up a server in less than 30 minutes unless anything uncommon is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the software deployments, we use &lt;a title=&quot;Capistrano&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/capistrano/capistrano&quot;&gt;Capistrano&lt;/a&gt;. This open-source tool is used to automate software deployments without downtime. Fast and simple. It is actually an awesome way to deliver our customers the latest version of their apps seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Maintenance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased we know that sometimes things might go wrong. Most of the times, the real cause of a general failure is an error that goes unnoticed for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our servers run very different services that need to be monitored (Nginx, MySQL, Elasticsearch… just to name a few!), so we use &lt;a title=&quot;Monit&quot; href=&quot;http://mmonit.com/monit/&quot;&gt;Monit&lt;/a&gt; to rule them all. Monit sends notifications whenever there is a risk of something failing such as a service being too loaded. It actually allows us to act proactively before any errors arise. But if a service goes down, Monit automatically tries to start it to minimize the downtime as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Monit itself is very impressive, we also use another error-tracking tool very known by the Ruby community. Airbrake is an exception reporting service &lt;a title=&quot;Airbrake&quot; href=&quot;https://airbrake.io/&quot;&gt;trusted by over 40k customers&lt;/a&gt;, now seamlessly integrated with our tech stack. Simply put, if anyone using our web applications comes across an error message, we&amp;#39;ll get a notification in our cell phones with the details of the error in less than a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing is more satisfying than spotting and solving bugs before users have even time to report them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s all for today, folks. As you can see, we love talking technologies. Feel free to drop us an e-mail or bring up a conversation on &lt;a title=&quot;MarsBased Twitter Profile&quot; href=&quot;http://twitter.com/MarsBased&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; anytime.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 16:59:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/03/24/we-make-the-right-app2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.marsbased.com/blog/2014/03/24/we-make-the-right-app2</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>