<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MarsBased</title>
    <description>MarsBased is an application development company in Barcelona, highly specialized in Ruby on Rails.</description>
    <link>https://www.marsbased.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.marsbased.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Expanding the MarsBased Team (Again)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d501.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so happy to announce that we’re expanding the MarsBased team again. We kicked off 2016 gracefully with three new projects and a good forecast for the months to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll frame this so you can understand it better. We usually get a new client every two or three months. The projects we do are big enough to sustain this. Also, we work with fewer clients, because we also carefully select them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our clients value our quality-over-quantity attitude, our fluid communication skills, our long-term relationships, and trust us to come up with high-caliber solutions where they only see uncertainty and difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, you can only imagine what happens when you land three in the same month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily enough, we’ve been harvesting our network for almost three years now. Not only have we organised many events, but we also attend developers’ meetups and keep in touch with the community via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupgrind.com/barcelona&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Grind&lt;/a&gt; or our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bcn-startups.com&quot; title=&quot;Startup community in Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Slack community for freelancers and Startups in Barcelona&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep a sustainable and organic growth within the company, we outsource part of our workload. This way, when we finish a project and have nothing ready on our pipeline, we take the outsourced projects in-house. If we didn’t do this, we couldn’t grow as we’ve done, and we probably would have had to shrink the team accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides that, outsourcing has also earned us the possibility to get to know brilliant individuals with whom we are very happy to work. This way, we worked with Mortensen in three or four different projects at the beginning, so when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/pedrogpimenta&quot; title=&quot;Pedro twitter handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pedro&lt;/a&gt; decided to quit their company, we approached him to hire him right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company is built upon trust, and recruitment is not an exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/blog-oriol1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Rocket launch&quot; title=&quot;Rocket launch&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Our team keeps growing. The spaceship gets bigger.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, we hired someone we have known for quite a long time. He was the first person to join Startup Circle when we created it, even before we launched MarsBased. We’ve been friends ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to welcome &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/oriol_bcn&quot; title=&quot;Oriol&#39;s Twitter handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Oriol&lt;/a&gt; to MarsBased. His experience in Rails and his previous experience as CTO at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dineyo.com&quot; title=&quot;Dineyo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dineyo&lt;/a&gt; will give a real boost to our already wonderful team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Oriol was among the attendees last week at the first open Ironhack talks, where I was honoured to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/ironhack-barcelona/events/228228599/&quot; title=&quot;Ironhack talk about MarsBased&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the first speaker&lt;/a&gt;. About 50 people showed up, amongst which I found some familiar faces from the community we’re building around our company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some background: Almost two years ago &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2014/08/22/The-Martians-conquer-the-IronHack/&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased conquers the Ironhack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;I gave the first talk about MarsBased at Ironhack&lt;/a&gt;. I was invited to talk about our experience, even though the company was barely a month old, so I spoke about what I knew from my previous companies and my failed ventures before MarsBased. Back then, these keynotes were only for Ironhack students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, I did this keynote with the lessons learnt during our first two years at MarsBased. Two years. Two years and 9 employees later. Who would’ve thought, when I quit my previous job in December 2013, that we’d reach this far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/blog-oriol2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Àlex talking at Ironhack&quot; title=&quot;Àlex talking at Ironhack&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Àlex talking at Ironhack.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, not many people knew MarsBased before the talk, only about ten, but in spite of that, 50 people showed up to learn from us. That was inspiring for me, and I hope it was also inspirational for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time to start telling the tale. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d like to hear your story too! If you’ve known us for a while, feel free to share what things you’ve learnt from us. If you didn’t know us, connect with us on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2016 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2016/02/21/Expanding-the-MarsBased-team-again</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2016/02/21/Expanding-the-MarsBased-team-again</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our New Year&#39;s Resolutions for 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d480.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some days ago we published what had been keeping us busy in 2015. Lots of projects, events, growing the team, getting clients from abroad, new learnings and heaps of experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that in mind, we&amp;#39;ve written the New Year&amp;#39;s Resolutions for this 2016, just like we did last year. Here&amp;#39;s the &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/01/20/Our-New-Years-Resolutions-For-20154&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased 2015 Resolutions&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;post with our 2015 Resolutions&lt;/a&gt;. Continue reading to find out what we&amp;#39;ll be up to on 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In no particular order, here&amp;#39;s what the Martians pledged to achieve in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/20160129 team.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Team playing&quot; title=&quot;Team playing&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Our team keeps growing, and sport is among our top priorities this year!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Xavier Redó - CTO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funnily enough, last year I introduced him with this sentence, which is also valid this year: &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;This past year has seen Xavi working hard to cope with all the projects we&amp;#39;ve gotten at MarsBased, therefore his resolutions are&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/xavi-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Xavier Redó&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Redó&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Xavier Redó&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CTO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Since we&#39;ve grown our team, we need to reduce the team&#39;s dependence on me so they can be more autonomous and I won&#39;t be a bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We will most likely meet this goal if I design a continuous training program. Every month we&#39;ll be learning something new.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;On a personal side, I&#39;ll become a father soon, so I am planning to find better life-work balance to enjoy both at their fullest. This will allocate more time to do sport and lead a healthier lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Finally, I&#39;d like to commit to learning mobile development during 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Francisco Javier López - Developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fran joined us in September 2015 as a Rails developer. He&amp;#39;s permanently based in Murcia, thus becoming the first 100% remote employee of the company. We fly him to Barcelona for the Martian Days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote right-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/fran.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Francisco Javier López&quot; title=&quot;Francisco Javier López&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Francisco Javier López&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Developer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Although I have been working with Rails for quite some time, I would like to consolidate my skills by trying to improve every project I work on.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I want to also contribute to open source by creating a couple of gems this year, and also some pull requests on popular repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;While I am fairly skilled with Ruby on Rails, I need to get hands on with AngularJS, as it&#39;s totally unknown to me.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Also, I usually retweet interesting stuff about coding, which gives ideas to Àlex for the MarsBased twitter handle, so I will keep doing that.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Other things that I feel I need to work on during 2016 are my English skills and practising sport on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Javier Pérez - Developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javi is the first hire at MarsBased. He&amp;#39;s been a year and a half with us already. Time flies!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/javi-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Javier Pérez&quot; title=&quot;Javier Pérez&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Javier Pérez&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Developer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I feel like I have learnt a lot in a year and a half coding in Rails, and I have started building projects from the ground up. I have also mastered AngularJS, so I will be defining and helping to adopt style guides within the company to standardise our projects.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;My weakest skill is the server provisioning and stage setup. I want to dedicate a lot of time this year to improve these skills in order to be more helpful in our different projects when it&#39;s time to set up the different stages.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This will also help ease Xavi&#39;s daily workload, as he will be delegating more stuff onto me.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;On a personal side, I want to become the world champion of paddle tennis, beat my teammates in every conceivable PS4 game there is, improve my spoken English, become a morning person and last, but not least, I&#39;ll try hard to not become single again!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Àlex Rodríguez - CMO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past year has seen me become Regional Director at Startup Grind, which I have to balance with my business development responsibilities at MarsBased. Now I look forward to taking MarsBased to the next level!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote right-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/alex-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Àlex Rodríguez&quot; title=&quot;Àlex Rodríguez&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Àlex Rodríguez&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CMO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I am happy to say that I am fully devoted now to what I like to do: sales and marketing. Throughout 2015, I had to help here and there, mostly on operational tasks and some project management, but I am happy to leave that behind.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I haven&#39;t learnt graphic editing, as intended, but I don&#39;t regret it. Instead, I&#39;ve learnt other useful stuff and I&#39;ve definitely honed my blogging and public speaking skills.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In 2016, I want to bring MarsBased to the next level: focus on getting new clients from outside Spain. I might have to grow this part of the team, but it&#39;ll pay off.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;As for Startup Grind, I want to have at least 100 people in every event and become THE event for startups and entrepreneurs in Barcelona. I also want to find more opportunities for our team to talk at big events.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Jordi Vendrell - COO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordi has combined his first year full-time at MarsBased with having co-founded his first child, Roger. He&amp;#39;s the one that best embodies the &lt;i&gt;quality&lt;/i&gt; aspect of MarsBased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/jordi-squared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jordi Vendrell&quot; title=&quot;Jordi Vendrell&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Jordi Vendrell&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;COO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;My main task at MarsBased is to improve everyone&#39;s working methodologies and the communications. Therefore, I designed our new working style, that will see us transition from being ninjas to samurais. I will blog about it very soon!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In the last months, I&#39;ve been helping out in the sales process, to improve the frequency of getting new clients. I want to continue doing so and offer value where needed.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I want to become more regular at sport. I&#39;ve had my streaks, but not very consistently. Balancing work and life with children is not always easy!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I want to work fewer hours, but more meaningful and focused hours. I want to keep it at 40 hours per week, which, for a founder, is not easy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;David Gómez - Developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David joined MarsBased at the end of 2015 Q1 and has been mainly working on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.naiz.eus&quot; title=&quot;Naiz&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Naiz&lt;/a&gt; project. He used to work with Javi and Àlex at VASS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote right-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/fotografia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;David Gómez&quot; title=&quot;David Gómez&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Gómez&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Developer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Although I had worked some time with Rails and Javascript before joining MarsBased, I was never at this level. Therefore, I want to continue growing my Rails and Javascript skills, especially with AngularJS and React.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I want to spend time writing on StackOverflow, which will help me to learn more coding, contribute to the community and also improve my written English skills.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This year I want to start really early to finish my working shift by lunchtime. That will allow me to have more time for side projects, such as launching my first mobile app with Ionic framework and learning AngularJS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Xavier Simó - Developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xavier, not Xavi, joined right after David, at the end of 2015 Q1, from Ironhack. He&amp;#39;s a pianist and you might remember him from his first &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/10/05/Code-Refactoring-When-Why-And-Who&quot; title=&quot;Code Reviews at MarsBased&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;blog post about code reviews&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote left-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/xavier.png&quot; alt=&quot;Xavier Simó&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Simó&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Xavier Simó&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Developer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I want to commit this new year to work on DevOps - with a special emphasis on Docker - and testing. I have worked a little bit here and there, but I feel there&#39;s a lot of room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I also feel I could bring more value to the company by learning how to estimate tasks better.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Like my buddies, I also want to learn how to manage my time better, so as to have a more balanced life, practise sport regularly and to plan my escape to a foreign country. I want to spend some time abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Pedro Pimenta - Frontend Developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met Pedro when he was working at Mortensen, with whom we collaborated in three or four projects, mostly during 2014. He&amp;#39;s Portuguese but lives in Barcelona. Well... he recently moved for some months to Mexico. Perks of being a remote company!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote right-sided&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/pedro.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pedro Pimenta&quot; title=&quot;Pedro Pimenta&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-circle&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pedro Pimenta&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Frontend Developer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;text&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;My self-organisation skills need to be taken to the next level this year: how to name stuff, what tools to use and when to work and when not. This will help me to be more productive.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Technology wise, I want to hone my CSS knowledge, being animations and flexbox my top priorities. Venturing into the Javascript world is also quite appealing, but that looks like stuff for 2017, because:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I&#39;m maximising my travel schedule when I am not working. In the past, I was quite overworked, so I feel like chilling a bit in my spare time in 2016. I might use this time to figure out how to live without a home, like a true digital nomad.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s to hoping that all this traveling and soul-seeking will help me to find more focus on what I do, read more (I bought a Kindle!), write more and quit smoking!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, comparing this year&amp;#39;s resolutions to last year&amp;#39;s, not only does the team grow, but also our ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your resolutions for 2016? Let&amp;#39;s comment them in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2016/01/31/Our-New-Years-Resolutions-for-2016</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2016/01/31/Our-New-Years-Resolutions-for-2016</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Looking Back to 2015: A Year out of This World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d478.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boy, what a year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/04/13/Lessons-Learned-One-Year-Running-Our-Own-Business/&quot; title=&quot;Lessons Learnt at MarsBased after the first year&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2014 was the year when MarsBased got real&lt;/a&gt;, 2015 has been a year of growth. If you want to know what has been keeping us busy this past year, keep reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/20160128 lookingback.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;All the road we&#39;ve covered&quot; title=&quot;All the road we&#39;ve covered&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Glancing back at 2015 feels like we&amp;#39;ve been covered great distances!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MarsBased has grown quite a lot. First of all, we started 2015 with only three full-time employees and an intern, &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/03/24/An-Internship-Out-of-This-World&quot; title=&quot;Emilio&#39;s Internship at MarsBased&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Emilio&lt;/a&gt;. However, during 2015, the third co-founder jumped in, and we hired &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dvdgs88&quot; title=&quot;David Gómez Twitter Handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;David&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/xsimov&quot; title=&quot;Xavier Simó twitter handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Xavier&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pedrogpimenta&quot; title=&quot;Pedro Pimenta twitter handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pedro&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fjsanpedro&quot; title=&quot;Fran&#39;s twitter handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fran&lt;/a&gt;. Despite this growth, we still continue being an office-less company: Pedro just moved to Mexico, Jordi works from Balaguer, Fran is permanently based in his hometown in Murcia and I keep working from European islands whenever I can, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/20160128soparnadal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The MarsBased team as of December 2015&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased team as of December 2015&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;The MarsBased team as of December 2015!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Back, left to right: Fran, Àlex, Xavi. Front, also left to right: Pedro, Xavier, David, Javi, Jordi.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides that, we have also been working more and more with our favourite freelancers and providers to give more and better services to our customers. Being a specialised dev shop has limitations as to which services can you offer. Luckily enough, we can count an amazing selection of professionals that can complement our Ruby on Rails &amp;amp; AngularJS expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read our &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/01/20/Our-New-Years-Resolutions-For-2015/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased 2015 New Year Resolutions&quot;&gt;2015 Resolutions post&lt;/a&gt;, you will see that we have been too busy to keep up with them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Our projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During 2015, we have not only enlarged the team, but also the project list, and, therefore our portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have had the pleasure of developing and launching really interesting and challenging projects such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://list71.com/&quot; title=&quot;List71&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;List71&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.skindler.com/&quot; title=&quot;Skindler&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Skindler&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eureka-experts.com/&quot; title=&quot;Eureka Experts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Eureka Experts&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://w28.bcn.cat/futurisme/&quot; title=&quot;FuTurisme&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;FuTurisme&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pisosbancos.com/&quot; title=&quot;PisosBancos&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PisosBancos&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.subastasde.com/&quot; title=&quot;SubastasDe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SubastasDe&lt;/a&gt; and a couple of others. We also became providers for &lt;a href=&quot;https://es.wuaki.tv/&quot; title=&quot;Wuaki.tv&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wuaki.tv&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://worldsensing.com/&quot; title=&quot;Worldsensing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Worldsensing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.naiz.eus/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Naiz&quot;&gt;Naiz&lt;/a&gt;, just to name a few. Some we can&amp;#39;t mention because of NDAs or other commercial agreements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the largest and most challenging have been List71 and Skindler. In the first one, an investment platform based on revenue, we had to learn how to deal with investment rounds, security compliance to treat banking data and an extremely polished UX that would help investors lend money to revenue-generating companies worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second case, Skindler is a curated marketplace of game development talent. Throughout this project, we have learnt how to pivot many times without breaking existing stuff, as we have had to change the design, layouts, main workflows and even the business model! We have mastered the lean startup methodology in this project. In fact, this is our oldest ongoing project: we have been working on it for almost two years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, we&amp;#39;ve worked on about a dozen projects during last year. That is, almost one a month!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cases, we had to deal with legacy code, but in most of them, we were able to build this using our Rails-powered tech stack. But most of all, it fills our Martian hearts with pride to have been able to work for clients from different countries, such as the USA, UK and Singapore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Building community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been very actively involved with the Barcelona startup community. It goes a long way back, even to some months before creating MarsBased, when &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2013/11/07/startup-circle-barcelona&quot; title=&quot;Startup Circle in Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;we started the Startup Circle community&lt;/a&gt; in Barcelona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/09/21/Five-Reasons-Why-Your-Company-Should-Organise-an-Event/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;We pulled the plug on Startup Circle&quot;&gt;we pulled the plug on Startup Circle&lt;/a&gt;, as we felt it had too much in common with Startup Grind, so we ended up merging them. If you want to go fast, go alone. If you want to go far, go together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupgrind.cat&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind BCN&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Grind&lt;/a&gt;, we have completed twelve more events (one every month, no exceptions!) upping the average attendance to 85 people, maxing at 180 in the event with the Wallapop founder Miguel Vicente. The event has also grown, as we&amp;#39;ve welcomed three new volunteers and have therefore enlarged the family. Also, I have been appointed as Regional Director for Southern Europe. So now I am responsible for Startup Grind Chapters in Spain, Portugal, Italy, Austria and Switzerland, in addition to those on Mars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past 2015 has seen us launching a very ambitious project: &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/10/26/We-Launched-Slack-For-The-Barcelona-Startup-Community/&quot; title=&quot;A Slack community for entrepreneurs and startups in Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a Slack-powered online community for all entrepreneurs and startups in Barcelona&lt;/a&gt;. As of today, it has 230 users exchanging jobs, hiring one another, arranging meetups, crowdsourcing ideas and doing all sorts of cool ideas. You can join it here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bcn-startups.com&quot; target=&quot;Barcelona community for startups and entrepreneurs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.bcn-startups.com&lt;/a&gt; (free and open for everyone!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/20160128xaviatgrind.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Our CTO Xavi giving a keynote at Startup Grind&quot; title=&quot;Our CTO Xavi giving a keynote at Startup Grind&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Our CTO Xavi giving a keynote at Startup Grind&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, but not least, we have been giving keynotes, mentoring and teaching at very distinct places such as Toulouse Business School, Universitat de Barcelona, IronHack, Makers of Barcelona, Conector, Salto con Red and many others! We also appeared in the press a couple of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A promising start&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While last year we focused on growing our team and helping to get the word out about what we do and who we are, this year we need to consolidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2016 will be the year where we settle all our methodologies we&amp;#39;ve been polishing and ironing out during 2015. This is the year that will see us becoming samurais, for we have been ninjas hacking our way up, until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, we have had a terrific start of 2016. Three new clients have trusted us to build their applications, from three different countries. We might as well want to prioritise getting projects from abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, it looks like we&amp;#39;ve got a bright future ahead. Oh, by the way, did we mention we&amp;#39;re launching a new website very soon? Stay tuned for updates!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would also like to hear about your 2015 experiences! What was your best moment? Feel free to share it in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2016 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2016/01/29/Looking-Back-to-2015-A-Year-Out-of-this-World</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2016/01/29/Looking-Back-to-2015-A-Year-Out-of-this-World</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Build CSS Grids: Floats vs Inline Blocks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d447.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased we&amp;#39;re very keen on sharing everything we learn. That&amp;#39;s why we recently published our &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/11/16/The-MarsBased-CSS-HTML-Guidelines/&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased HTML &amp; CSS Guidelines&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HTML &amp;amp; CSS Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, and our &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/05/13/The-MarsBased-Blogging-Guide&quot; title=&quot;How to create a damn good blog post&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;blogging tips&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/04/13/Lessons-Learned-One-Year-Running-Our-Own-Business&quot; title=&quot;Lessons learnt after being one year in business&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lessons learnt in our first year running the company&lt;/a&gt;, among other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this entry, you will learn how to build CSS grids by comparing the two most popular approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;#39;re building anything in CSS (a header, a form or a grid, just to name a few) the first thing you need to consider is how elements will react with each other. That&amp;#39;s how the flow of the document works: you put elements next to each other and you tell them how to behave. Some properties you attach to an element have an influence on the elements beside it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Floated elements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s say you want to build a simple 3-column layout like this one:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post28a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Simple 3 column layout&quot; title=&quot;Simple 3 column layout&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First you write your HTML, which in this case is very simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;row&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;item&amp;quot;&amp;gt;item&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;item&amp;quot;&amp;gt;item&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;item&amp;quot;&amp;gt;item&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for the CSS, the most common way to tackle this is to &lt;code&gt;float&lt;/code&gt; these elements, which means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;.item {
    display: block;
    width: 33.33%;
    float: left;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means all objects will float to the left in relation to each other. The first problem that we get here is this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post28b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Floating error&quot; title=&quot;Floating error&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now, their parent &lt;code&gt;.row&lt;/code&gt; doesn&amp;#39;t have a height, because floating an object means it will only &amp;quot;interact&amp;quot; with others that are floating. &lt;code&gt;.row&lt;/code&gt; is not floating, so it will not take its floated child elements into account. To overcome this, we have to start &amp;quot;hacking&amp;quot; using one of the following options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can apply &lt;code&gt;overflow: hidden;&lt;/code&gt; to the parent. This may work as intended in our example, but maybe you can&amp;#39;t use this, but you may need to have a different value for &lt;code&gt;overflow&lt;/code&gt; for some other reason.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can float the &lt;code&gt;.row&lt;/code&gt;. This way, because it is floated, it will take its children&amp;#39;s height into account and properly grow as needed. But maybe this option isn&amp;#39;t available for you either, in which case it&amp;#39;s getting difficult to overcome this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can set the &lt;code&gt;.row&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;display: inline-block;&lt;/code&gt;, which will also take the children into account, but maybe you need it to be &lt;code&gt;display: block;&lt;/code&gt; for some other reason.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I&amp;#39;ve recently learned, you can add two pseudo-elements (&lt;code&gt;:before&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;:after&lt;/code&gt;) to the parent &lt;code&gt;.row&lt;/code&gt; and set them as &lt;code&gt;display: table;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;clear: both;&lt;/code&gt; to fix this. But, then again, if you also want to add some pseudo-element to do something else visually, this is not an option for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these is bound to solve the parent height problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let&amp;#39;s say this is fixed and you want to add more items and build something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post28c.png&quot; alt=&quot;Simple 3 columns layout with 6 elements&quot; title=&quot;Simple 3 columns layout with 6 elements&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because the web is not static and you&amp;#39;ll never know how big the content of the &lt;code&gt;.item&lt;/code&gt; elements will be (unless you force it), you can have items with different heights. If that&amp;#39;s the case, this will eventually occur:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post28d.png&quot; alt=&quot;Floated height wrapping error&quot; title=&quot;Floated height wrapping error&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Item 3 is smaller than Item 2, so Item 4 will be rendered under 3, and that&amp;#39;s not right. So here we get back to &amp;quot;hacking&amp;quot;, we need to make it so every third item starting from the fourth is forced to jump to the next line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;.item:nth-child(3n+4) {
    clear: left;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if, suddenly, we want to have 4 columns, we have to change that rule as well. This is not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Inline Blocks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we&amp;#39;ve seen, using floated elements has its quirks or may not be an option for you, so let&amp;#39;s see how you can use &lt;code&gt;inline-block&lt;/code&gt; as an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to give you a quick intro, &lt;code&gt;display: inline-block;&lt;/code&gt; makes elements flow like text though each one will still be a block (in contrast, if you use &lt;code&gt;display: inline;&lt;/code&gt; your elements will flow like text but will not have width or height, only the dimensions of its contents). This means that elements put side-by-side will display side-by-side as long as they fit within their parent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, let&amp;#39;s do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;.item {
    display: inline-block;
    width: 33.33%;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method also needs a small hack to circumvent the following problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post28e.png&quot; alt=&quot;Font size error with inline-block&quot; title=&quot;Font size error with inline-block&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is happening here is that &lt;code&gt;inline-block&lt;/code&gt; elements behave like words and, as words, they have &lt;code&gt;word-spacing&lt;/code&gt;, which is a natural space between words. To overcome this, you can either reset the font-size on the parent (my favourite way, but with some shortcomings when you use &lt;code&gt;ems&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code&gt;font-size&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;.row {
    font-size: 0;
}
.item {
    font-size: 1rem;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can adjust the &lt;code&gt;word-spacing&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;.row {
    word-spacing: -4px;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;word-spacing&lt;/code&gt; value depends on the typeface you are using, but the rule is to always use the smallest negative spacing possible. And now we have a perfect grid:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post28f.png&quot; alt=&quot;Simple 3 column layout with inline-block&quot; title=&quot;Simple 3 column layout with inline-block&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this better? For one, you can change the number of columns without running into the layout issues we looked at earlier. But the best thing is being able to align items vertically:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post28g.png&quot; alt=&quot;Centering columns vertically&quot; title=&quot;Centering columns vertically&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just by doing this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;.item {
    vertical-align: middle;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn&amp;#39;t that great? There&amp;#39;s no good way to do that with floated elements. You can also set &lt;code&gt;vertical-align&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;top&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;bottom&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;baseline&lt;/code&gt;, among others, depending on what you want to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also set the container to &lt;code&gt;text-align: center;&lt;/code&gt; to achieve this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post28h.png&quot; alt=&quot;Centering columns horizontally&quot; title=&quot;Centering columns horizontally&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is useful for dynamic content where you don&amp;#39;t know how many items you will have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s not one good way to do it, that&amp;#39;s the problem and beauty of web technologies! There are loads of ways to do each and every little thing, but there are always nuances that lead you to choose one or the other. At MarsBased we use a mix of these two. We mostly use floats because we use Bootstrap&amp;#39;s grids to build general layouts, but we sometimes resort to use the &lt;code&gt;inline-block&lt;/code&gt; technique when we need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also some CSS grid systems based on &lt;code&gt;inline-block&lt;/code&gt; that are worth taking a look at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://necolas.github.io/griddle/&quot; title=&quot;Griddle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Griddle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.justifygrid.com/&quot; title=&quot;Justify Grid&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Justify Grid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the future is very promising, and we&amp;#39;re keeping an eye on &lt;a href=&quot;http://learnlayout.com/flexbox.html&quot; title=&quot;Flexbox&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Flexbox&lt;/a&gt;, which gives us new ways to address these issues. Maybe the next front-end post will be about forgetting all of this and using the Flex Box model instead!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/12/28/How-To-Build-CSS-Grids-Floats-VS-Inline-Blocks</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/12/28/How-To-Build-CSS-Grids-Floats-VS-Inline-Blocks</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Handle Client Work Remotely: Our Communication Stack</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d427.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a remote working company, we work from &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/06/22/Working-Remotely-from-Berlin/&quot; title=&quot;Working remotely from Berlin&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;very different places&lt;/a&gt; and at very different times. That is, we have no office. Because of that, we face a lot of questions about how we deal with customers: &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;How do you earn their trust?&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;how can they know if you&amp;#39;re working?&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;how do you deal with specification changes?&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dealing with clients while being a remote working company is not easy. In this entry, we explain how we do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, it is easier for product companies to offer full flexibility on where and when to work, but not so much in service companies. For instance, Red Hat, Github, Spotify, Buffer and Basecamp - just to name a few - are companies that offer full-remote positions. Service companies offering remote positions do exist, but they’re fewer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;During the length of the project, I’ve talked to you more often than to my colleagues in the office, and I’ve only seen you once!&lt;/i&gt; - One of our clients&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to manage client work by being 100% remote is to be the best at communication. And how do you become the best at communicating? With a solid &lt;i&gt;communication stack&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What is a communication stack?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tech-oriented companies often define their &lt;i&gt;tech stack&lt;/i&gt;, which is the tools &amp;amp; programming languages they use as a &lt;i&gt;de facto&lt;/i&gt; standard for every new project. One of the most famous tech stacks is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LAMP_(software_bundle)&quot; title=&quot;LAMP&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;LAMP architecture&lt;/a&gt; (Linux, Apache, MySQL, Php).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, a communication stack is the tool belt you use to channel company communications, both internal and external.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal communication&lt;/strong&gt; includes project management, news sharing, a chatroom, decision taking and transfer of knowledge within your team. Think of your project management tools, task list managers, corporate chats/social networks, organisation tools, wikis, storage platforms, intranets and video call rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External communication&lt;/strong&gt;, instead, refers to whatever channels and tools you use to interact with agents outside of your company. That includes the following: RSS, newsletter &amp;amp; emailing tools, social media, call centers, a blog, newsfeeds, forums and client management tools. Some of the tools mentioned in the internal communication side might also be used here, as some allow collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In product companies, this separation is clearer, but as a services company, the limits between internal and external are far more diffuse. In this entry, we will focus more on the tools themselves than whether they&amp;#39;re for internal or for external communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get to it. We’ll describe how do we manage our client work remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Project Management: Basecamp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post27a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Overview of Basecamp&quot; title=&quot;Overview of Basecamp&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;This is how a Project looks like on Basecamp&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.basecamp.com&quot; title=&quot;Basecamp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Basecamp&lt;/a&gt; is an online collaboration tool for team management. The reason why we like Basecamp so much is because they’re the creators of the framework Ruby on Rails and the writers of two really inspirational books we identify ourselves a lot with, both as individuals and as a company: &lt;a href=&quot;https://37signals.com/rework/&quot; title=&quot;Rework&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Rework&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://37signals.com/remote/&quot; title=&quot;Remote: No Office Required&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Remote: No Office Required&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basecamp focuses on simplicity to provide a solid tool that allows the management of almost any team. In fact, we don’t use it only for our internal team, but we also manage our client work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have created a project for each and every project we’ve got. In client projects, we keep our clients in the loop by inviting them to join the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basecamp is really good to centralise a project’s relevant information in just one place. All discussions should be placed here, and decisions too. If something has been agreed outside of Basecamp, it should be moved to Basecamp, lest we forget about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also use the Google Drive integration to attach the important project files to the Basecamp Project (contracts, offers, credentials, documentation, logos, mockups etc.) and their own text files to save things you don’t want anyone to forget about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we also use Basecamp to include our weekly report - every Monday - of what has been keeping us busy the previous week, and the planning for the week ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post27c.png&quot; alt=&quot;Reporting on Basecamp&quot; title=&quot;Reporting on Basecamp&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;You can use Basecamp to send the weekly reports to your clients&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sprints &amp;amp; Tech teams: Trello + Github&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post27d.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Trello board&quot; title=&quot;A Trello board&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;This is the top part of the sprint funnel on Trello&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://trello.com&quot; title=&quot;Trello&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; is our tool of choice to manage team tasks. It&amp;#39;s 100% agile-oriented and, therefore, a good fit for agile development teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trello boards allow you to create lists that hold cards. Each list represents a status, and the cards are dragged from board to board as they change their status. In the screenshot above, you can see some of the lists distributing the tasks between &lt;i&gt;Backlog&lt;/i&gt;, the &lt;i&gt;Features&lt;/i&gt; list, the &lt;i&gt;Bugs&lt;/i&gt; list, and the planning for the next week. In the screenshot below, you can also see the lists including the tasks that have already been completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post27e.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Trello board&quot; title=&quot;A Trello board&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;This is the bottom part of the sprint funnel on Trello&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tasks that have been completed by our developers are placed into the &lt;i&gt;Review Pending&lt;/i&gt; list, where a more experienced developer or the person in charge of code review will review them and test them. Once OK’d, they are dragged to the &lt;i&gt;Done&lt;/i&gt; list. Should one of them not be OK enough to be deployed, it’s moved back to the current week and reassigned to the developer so he spends more time on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like to take this a little further, and we also classify the tasks &amp;amp; features according to where they are deployed. This works really well to find out very quickly what features are available in which environment, so we don’t miss stuff during product demos. For that, we&amp;#39;ve got lists such as &lt;i&gt;Deployed to staging&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Deployed to production&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the inside of a card, you can describe the task at hand, label it according to whatever taxonomy you use, assign it to people, add attachments, comment on the task and set a due date, among other things. We use the comments system to include the pull request of that feature/bug/hotfix when the task is completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post27f.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Trello card&quot; title=&quot;A Trello card&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Trello cards represent tasks or sets of similar tasks&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Trello is very oriented to tech-savvy people, we only invite the technical personnel of our clients: CTOs, developers, tech leads and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Real-time communication: Slack&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While all the previous tools are really good for taking decisions, planning and execution, none of them offers real-time communication. For that, we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slack.com&quot; title=&quot;Slack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;: a real-time communication tool for teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post27g.png&quot; alt=&quot;Slack&quot; title=&quot;Slack&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Here&amp;#39;s our COO Jordi reporting to one of our clients via Slack&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some clients demand a higher availability and/or a really short response time. For them, we set up a new Slack team, so everyone’s on board and can have direct real-time communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this fast and effective communication is good for the coordination of urgent actions (hotfixes, a demo day, or other emergencies), Slack&amp;#39;s free tier only retains the last 10000 messages. Therefore, all decisions taken on Slack are volatile. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NOW4QiOD-oc&quot; title=&quot;Blade Runner Monologue&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;All those moments will be lost in time, like tears...in...rain&lt;/a&gt;. For exceptional clients, we set up the paid version of Slack and channel all communication through Slack. We&amp;#39;re flexible about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack also provides kickass integrations with some of our preferred tools. You can integrate it with almost whatever tool your company or project uses. Depending on the project, we integrate it with Airbrake, Trello, Github or Bug Catcher just to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With their multi-platform &amp;amp; -device apps, you’re just a chat away from getting an answer (or a question) from your client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Videocalls: Appear.in&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some topics require a little bit more of human touch. To be more precise, certain matters require a face-to-face conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some text messages just don’t add the criticality, urgency or calm that a face-to-face conversation has. As a remote working company, it might as well happen that we are on the other side of the world when talking to our clients. But luckily enough, we’ve got &lt;a href=&quot;http://appear.in&quot; title=&quot;Appear.in&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Appear.in&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post27h.png&quot; alt=&quot;Appear.in&quot; title=&quot;Appear.in&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;We kindly borrowed this photo from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/appear_in/status/560023198226714624&quot; title=&quot;Appear.in Twitter handle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@appearin&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt; Twitter!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appear.in excels in what other video call services fail to deliver: requires no registering, no accounts, no installation and no hassle what-so-ever. Just type in &lt;i&gt;http://appear.in/(NAMEOFYOURCHATROOM)&lt;/i&gt; and boom! You’re magically in. Up to eight people joining that URL will be placed in a group video conference with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, we also have found that the video quality and the call stability is much better than on Skype or Google Hangouts, thus making it ideal for people in low wifi signals or using their mobile data plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, but not least, Appear.in also offers screen sharing options, which they’re good enough for most purposes. However, we sometimes need to have a more collaborative screen share so we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://screenhero.com&quot; title=&quot;Screenhero&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Screenhero&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our way to handle client work remotely! As you can see, there’s nothing that we can’t do with these tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d love to hear your thoughts on this, and what your communication stack is. What best practices do you recommend? What tools can we suggest we try to improve our current stack? Let’s discuss this in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/12/07/How-to-Handle-Client-Work-Remotely-Our-Communication-Stack</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/12/07/How-to-Handle-Client-Work-Remotely-Our-Communication-Stack</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The MarsBased CSS &amp; HTML Guidelines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d406.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we started MarsBased, we&amp;#39;ve completed a good share of projects. From all of them we&amp;#39;ve learnt something useful. But all this knowledge should be stored somewhere for further use, for instance, to train new developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much like we did with the release of the MarsBased blogging guide (&lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/05/13/The-MarsBased-Blogging-Guide&quot; title=&quot;How to Create a Damn Good Blog Post&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/08/16/How-to-Create-a-Blogging-Strategy-for-your-Company&quot; title=&quot;How to Create a Blogging Strategy for Your Company&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;), we want to share what we have learnt about HTML5 &amp;amp; CSS3 with you all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things should not only work well. They can also look good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frontend developers, this one is for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Workflows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we delve into the technologies we use, we will introduce our working methodologies here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Task management&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trello.com&quot; title=&quot;Trello&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; is our tool of choice for managing tasks and weekly sprints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have one board for each project. Inside the project&amp;#39;s board, you&amp;#39;ll find columns for the present and coming weeks, along with &lt;i&gt;Done, Review Pending, Bugs, Features,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Backlog&lt;/i&gt;. In projects that have been already rolled out, you will see some columns for the deploys management, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Project Manager is in charge of assigning the layout &amp;amp; design tasks. You will see the cards assigned to you in the present week column. Once you have finished a task, you must add a new comment indicating the relevant pull request link, and move the card to the &lt;i&gt;Review&lt;/i&gt; Pending column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Project Manager will review the implementations and move the card to &lt;i&gt;Done&lt;/i&gt;, send it back to you (if there is something to fix) or forward it to the Development Team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weekly sprints are defined on Mondays, in an online meeting between you and the Project Manager. However, don&amp;#39;t hesitate to get in touch with the Project Manager at any time, if you need to discuss anything or have any question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Commits &amp; Branches&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work with both &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot; title=&quot;Github&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://bitbucket.org&quot; title=&quot;Bitbucket&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt; and we always have separate repositories for the layout implementation and the development, so you don&amp;#39;t have to worry about breaking stuff or learning Ruby on Rails. In other words, you will have to deal with HTML, CSS, and JS, only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we never work on the &lt;i&gt;master&lt;/i&gt; branch, as it only contains reviewed and finished stuff. Usually, we create a new branch for each task. However, we sometimes group small and related tasks to use only one branch for them. Apply common sense and branch wisely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Project Manager will merge those branches into &lt;i&gt;master&lt;/i&gt; after making the relevant reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, when we make commits, we always include the type of change we have made between brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you&amp;#39;ve changed only the CSS code, you indicate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[CSS] Replaced the body background color.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have changed the HTML and you have replaced some images, you will write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[HTML+IMG] Replaced the default avatar.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might want to include other indications like &lt;i&gt;JS, README, CONFIG,&lt;/i&gt; etc. This way, our developers will be able to identify very quickly what they have to change in the development to replicate our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Testing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quality is one of the founding values of MarsBased. A while back ago, we defined quality as &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;meeting and exceeding clients expectations while maintaining our own methodologies&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot;. For that reason, exhaustive and successful testing is critical in our day to day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a front end developer, you’re in charge of testing how the applications look in all the required browsers and devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our testing workflow is plain and simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In new projects where we start the development from scratch, we leave the testing tasks for the end and we do them all at once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In projects under maintenance (live products), we test each new feature or bug fix before sending the pull request to the development team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep this in mind all the time: an excellent developer is not just someone who creates good code, but is also a good tester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tech Stack and Guidelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Middleman&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://middlemanapp.com&quot; title=&quot;Middleman&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt; is a static websites generator built with Ruby on Rails. It integrates all the state-of-the-art frameworks and tools for frontend development (like SASS, Modernizr, Compass, Autoprefixer...) and allows you to use templating languages such as ERB or Liquid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All our new projects are developed using Middleman, but before that, we used &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot; title=&quot;Jekyll&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. Jekyll is very similar to Middleman, with only a few differences between them. While we used Liquid as the templating language in Jekyll, now we switched to ERB in Middleman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the project&amp;#39;s README file, you will find instructions about how to install the required packages and run any of those tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;MIDDLEMAN TOOLS&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Middleman lets you organize your code in layouts and partials. Do it wisely, we don&amp;#39;t want to have to deal with tons of files. Use partials only for stuff that will appear in several pages, or to split the code of very long pages, but always remember that &lt;i&gt;simpler is better&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have developed our own Middleman template called MarsMan. We use it as a model to create new projects. It contains all the folders, SASS mixins, frameworks and libraries that we use in our projects. Marsman is an open source project, so you can use it for your personal stuff or even send it to other people. You can download the code from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarsBased/marsman-template&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased Github profile&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;our Github profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We use the Middleman helper &lt;i&gt;page_classes&lt;/i&gt; to define &lt;i&gt;page-specific&lt;/i&gt; classes in the body tag of the HTML. Use them carefully, we don&amp;#39;t want to create too many page dependencies in our CSS code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Middleman has a very useful set of helpers that let you add random Lorem Ipsum content and image placeholders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Middleman allows you to add Markdown content to a website by simply including a markdown file as a partial inside any other HTML file. We use Markdown files for text-only pages like Terms &amp;amp; Conditions, Privacy Policy or blog posts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more information about Middleman and Jekyll in their official websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, if you never had the chance to use ERB, you can find some examples in &lt;a href=&quot;http://benfrain.com/understanding-middleman-the-static-site-generator-for-faster-prototyping/&quot; title=&quot;Middleman&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of our works are based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; title=&quot;Bootstrap&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s a very well-known markup framework and it offers good compatibility with browsers and other components. Also, our developers are familiar with it and can reuse a lot of code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tend to use always the last stable version of Bootstrap, in their SASS distribution. Since we also use SASS as our CSS framework of choice, you will be able to replace the Bootstrap variables and adapt them to each project. Do it whenever possible, instead of overwriting the Bootstrap properties. You can find the complete list of variables in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/twbs/bootstrap-sass/blob/master/assets/stylesheets/bootstrap/_variables.scss&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; title=&quot;Bootstrap SASS Github page&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bootstrap SASS Github page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Bootstrap has a very powerful grid system. It can be used by simply including classes in the HTML markup, such as &lt;i&gt;.row&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;.col-xs-6&lt;/i&gt;. However, instead of using those classes to define rows and columns, we prefer to use the Bootstrap mixins. They also allow you to define rows and columns, but you can do it directly in the SASS files, without dirtying the HTML code. Following this approach, we can completely separate the markup of a website from its styles and we make the application easier to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, instead of doing:
&lt;pre&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;container&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;results row&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;item col-xs-12 col-sm-6 col-md-4&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      The Martian
    &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We prefer to do:
&lt;pre&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;container&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;results&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;item&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      The Martian
    &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And:
&lt;pre&gt;
.results
  +make-row()
.item
  +make-xs-column(12)
  +make-sm-column(6)
  +make-md-column(4)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/twbs/bootstrap-sass/blob/master/assets/stylesheets/bootstrap/mixins/_grid.scss&quot; title=&quot;Mixins used in the grid system&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;mixins used in the grid system&lt;/a&gt; also in Github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;SASS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SASS is a CSS preprocessor that lets you use variables, functions, operations, and other useful stuff inside your CSS stylesheets. You can learn how to use SASS in their &lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/&quot; title=&quot;SASS official website&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;official website&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;#39;re sure you&amp;#39;ll find it very easy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;PARTIALS&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We organize our SASS code in partials that we later import in a single file called &lt;i&gt;application.sass&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These partials are organized in folders. Take a look at this example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
/stylesheets

  /utils
    _mixins.sass
    _variables.sass
    _helpers.sass
    _keyframes.sass

  /modules
    _navbar.sass
    _footer.sass
    _items.sass
    _filters.sass

  /layouts
    _home.sass
    _results.sass

  application.sass

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;/utils&lt;/i&gt; folder is where we store our helpers, mixins and keyframes - coding tools that we use in our HTML and SASS files. We also have a file called &lt;i&gt;_variables.sass&lt;/i&gt; that contains generic variables like color or typography definitions. However, page- or module-specific variables are not stored here but inside the corresponding layout or module file (you can find an example a couple of paragraphs from here).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;/modules&lt;/i&gt; folder contains the styles of the different components that compose each page. And finally, we use the &lt;i&gt;/layouts&lt;/i&gt; folder to include styles we need to apply to specific pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the difference between layouts and modules is still not clear for you, have a look at the following example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s say that we have to develop a marketplace with a results page, where each result is an item. Some of these items will also appear in the Home page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would create a &lt;i&gt;_items.sass&lt;/i&gt; file inside &lt;i&gt;/modules&lt;/i&gt; and we would put there all the styles that apply to the items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
// modules/_item.sass

.item

  $item-primary-color: #000000 // Variable specific to this module!

  padding: 20px
  background-color: #f4f4f4

  .title
    color: $item-primary-color
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now consider that these items have to look differently in the Homepage than in the Results view. In that case, we would create a &lt;i&gt;_home.sass&lt;/i&gt; file inside &lt;i&gt;/layouts&lt;/i&gt; with the following styles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
// modules/_home.sass

.home
  .item
    background-color: inherit
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;NAMING CONVENTIONS&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to name our elements and classes, we follow the modular approach explained in &lt;a href=&quot;http://thesassway.com/advanced/modular-css-naming-conventions&quot; title=&quot;Modular CSS naming conventions&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://thesassway.com/&quot; title=&quot;The SASS Way&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;The SASS Way&lt;/a&gt;. However, we don&amp;#39;t apply the &lt;i&gt;parent-child&lt;/i&gt; rules, as we prefer to use nesting for such cases. In any case, if you ever have to define parent-child relations, use a dash (-) as a separator instead of an underscore (_) or any other symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in order to differentiate keyframes (animations) from classes or IDs, we name them without dashes or underscores:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
// Keyframes

@keyframes fadeIn
  0%
    opacity: 0
  100%
    opacity: 1

@keyframes fadeOut
  0%
    opacity: 1
  100%
    opacity: 0
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;OTHER GUIDELINES&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can create your own mixins, but do it only when they will save you a lot of time, without adding too much complexity to the project. We don&amp;#39;t want to increase the application complexity because other less experienced coders might have to work on it at some point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nesting is one of the most powerful tools of SASS. However, it can be counterproductive if not used wisely. We follow the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thesassway.com/beginner/the-inception-rule&quot; title=&quot;The Inception Rule&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Inception Rule&lt;/a&gt; defined in The SASS Way. It says that you can&amp;#39;t go more than four levels deep. It also explains how to organize the different selectors and properties in site-wide rules, page specific rules and objects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In projects where we don&amp;#39;t have to support IE8 or lower, we use REM units to define font sizes, margins, heights, widths, etc. REM units work in a similar way than EMs, but they are proportional to the HTML tag &lt;i&gt;font-size&lt;/i&gt;. Bootstrap defines the HTML &lt;i&gt;font-size&lt;/i&gt; to 10px, so using REM units is very easy: 1rem will always be equal to 10px, 1.4rem will be equal to 14px, 0.8rem will be equal to 8px, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Autoprefixer, Modernizr, and Compass&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/middleman/middleman-autoprefixer&quot; title=&quot;Autoprefixer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Autoprefixer&lt;/a&gt; is a plugin that parses the CSS files and adds browser specific prefixes to the properties that require them. This means that you don&amp;#39;t have to worry about adding prefixes such as -webkit-, -moz- or -ms- because Autoprefixer does it for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://modernizr.com/&quot; title=&quot;Modernizr&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Modernizr&lt;/a&gt; is a JavaScript library that detects if the user&amp;#39;s browser supports HTML5 and CSS3 features or not. You can use it to build fallbacks for modern features that old browsers might not support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://compass-style.org/&quot; title=&quot;Compass&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Compass&lt;/a&gt; is another CSS framework included in our Middleman projects. We prefer to use Autoprefixer to add browser specific prefixes, but you might want to use Compass for other things, like its vast library of reliable mixins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Images and icons&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;VECTORIAL IMAGES&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For logos, icons and small images we prefer to use SVG files instead of PNGs or JPGs because SVGs are made from vectors and can be resized without losing quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To include SVG files in the HTML code, drop the SVG files in the &lt;i&gt;shapes&lt;/i&gt; directory. All SVG files are formatted in XML. Make sure that they don&amp;#39;t have more data than the necessary (some apps like Adobe Illustrator include irrelevant information inside the SVG files that can produce errors).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, you will have to execute a job that will take all the SVG files from the &lt;i&gt;shapes&lt;/i&gt; directory and produce a file called &lt;i&gt;shapes.html&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;grunt svg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This file should be included in all the app&amp;#39;s pages as a partial:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt; &amp;lt;body class=&amp;quot;&amp;lt;%= page_classes %&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;%= partial &amp;quot;partials/shapes&amp;quot; %&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;%= yield %&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;%= javascript_include_tag  :application %&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can include any SVG image in your HTML by simply calling it. Use this markup to do it so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;svg class=&amp;quot;shape shape-filename&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;use xlink:href=&amp;quot;#shape-filename&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/use&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/svg&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;BOOTSTRAP GLYPHICONS AND FONT AWESOME&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the design doesn&amp;#39;t come with its own icons, we like to use the ones provided by Bootstrap and Font Awesome. If you don&amp;#39;t find any suitable icon, try looking in websites like &lt;a href=&quot;http://iconfinder.com&quot; title=&quot;Iconfinder.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;iconfinder.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;IMAGE HELPERS&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cases, we will have to deal with normal images like PNGs or JPGs. In that case, we use the image-url helper in the CSS files to point to files stored in the images folder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;.navbar
  background: image-url(&amp;#39;navbar-background.png&amp;#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the HTML markup, however, we use another helper called &lt;i&gt;image_tag&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;%= image_tag &amp;#39;padrino.png&amp;#39;, width: &amp;#39;35&amp;#39;, class: &amp;#39;logo pull-right&amp;#39; %&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more examples of the &lt;i&gt;image_tag&lt;/i&gt; helper in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActionView/Helpers/AssetTagHelper.html#method-i-image_tag&quot; title=&quot;Ruby on Rails API documentation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Ruby on Rails API documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;JS libraries&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all the JS libraries work well with Rails and AngularJS. For that reason, and also because we like to standardize the code of our projects, we have created a list of preferred libraries. If you ever have to use another library, consult our Development Team first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Modals:&lt;/b&gt; ng-dialog (only in AngularJS projects) and Bootstrap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Dropdown menus:&lt;/b&gt; Bootstrap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Selects:&lt;/b&gt; Select2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tabs:&lt;/b&gt; Bootstrap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Carousels:&lt;/b&gt; Slick.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Checkbox and radio buttons:&lt;/b&gt; Pure CSS (label after the input technique).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Charts:&lt;/b&gt; C3 &amp;amp; D3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Autocomplete:&lt;/b&gt; Select2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Range sliders:&lt;/b&gt; bootstrap-slider.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Scroll:&lt;/b&gt; Just the browser scrollbar (avoid using JS scrollbars like Perfect Scrollbar if possible).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Affix &amp;amp; Scrollspy:&lt;/b&gt; Bootstrap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tooltips &amp;amp; popovers:&lt;/b&gt; Bootstrap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Alerts:&lt;/b&gt; Bootstrap + simple fade in with JS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Text editors:&lt;/b&gt; TinyMCE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Date management:&lt;/b&gt; MomentJS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Datepickers:&lt;/b&gt; Pickadate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Animations:&lt;/b&gt; Pure CSS. Velocity if more complex animations are needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Progress Bars:&lt;/b&gt; Pure CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Maps:&lt;/b&gt; Leaflet or Google Maps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Parallax:&lt;/b&gt; Pure CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Image galleries:&lt;/b&gt; Slick.js inside a modal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chat mentions:&lt;/b&gt; AT.js.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Code spacing and formatting guidelines&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;80 CHARACTERS PER LINE&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not always possible, but in order to improve code legibility we try to make lines no longer than 80 characters (this applies to HTML, JS, and SASS too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have to split an HTML tag, do it between attributes and indent the second line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a class=&amp;quot;item-link&amp;quot; href=&amp;quot;https://marsbased.com&amp;quot;
  target=&amp;quot;_blank&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  MarsBased Website
&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advanced text editors like Sublime Text allow you to add a ruler on your screen that mark where the 80 characters per line are reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;HTML FILES&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t include any extra line-breaks between &lt;i&gt;divs&lt;/i&gt; and other elements. Also, we avoid using HTML comments unless they are completely necessary to explain how something is supposed to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, instead of doing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;results&amp;quot;&amp;gt;

  &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;item&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;h2&amp;gt;MarsBased website&amp;lt;/h2&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;lt;!-- .item --&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;lt;!-- .results --&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We prefer to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;results&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;item&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;h2&amp;gt;MarsBased website&amp;lt;/h2&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bonus:&lt;/b&gt; there is a Sublime Text plugin called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SublimeText/TrailingSpaces&quot; title=&quot;TrailingSpaces&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;TrailingSpaces&lt;/a&gt; that detects unnecessary blank spaces in your code and deletes them all at once with a keyboard shortcut!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;SASS FILES&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a CSS selector doesn’t have any property inside it, we leave no space between the selector and the selector that comes next:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;.results
  .item
    border: 1px solid purple
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if a selector has some properties, we add an extra line break between the last property and the next selector:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;.results
padding: 10px 20px

.item
border: 1px solid purple
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;SEO&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We follow the SEO best practices of naming all the elements with HTML5 semantic tags, when possible, like &lt;i&gt;header, aside, section, nav, footer, article,&lt;/i&gt; etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside each of these tags, we try to respect a hierarchic structure of headings. It sounds obvious, but &lt;i&gt;h1&lt;/i&gt; elements must contain &lt;i&gt;h2&lt;/i&gt; and not the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we always add the &lt;i&gt;title&lt;/i&gt; attribute to all the links and &lt;i&gt;title&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;alt&lt;/i&gt; to all the images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en/docs/Sections_and_Outlines_of_an_HTML5_document&quot; title=&quot;HTML5 elements&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this website&lt;/a&gt; for a complete guide of HTML5 elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;LINKS BETWEEN PAGES&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our layouts are used by our programmers to understand how they have to develop an application. However, our clients use them too to review the status of a project and to show the user interface to other people like investors or partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that reason, we create navigational layouts linking all the pages and our projects can be used as a normal application (although the content is completely static). For example, if someone clicks the “Sign up” link of the navigation bar, we take him to the Sign Up page, where he will be able to check how it looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a long read, indeed! Have you learnt something useful? Do you want to add something? Let us know in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2015 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/11/16/The-MarsBased-CSS-HTML-Guidelines</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/11/16/The-MarsBased-CSS-HTML-Guidelines</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Presenting the Barcelona Startups Community on Slack</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d386.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack is the new trend in online communications. Given its free-for-all policy, all kinds of companies adopted this popular communication app as their &lt;i&gt;de facto&lt;/i&gt; communication platform. Slack is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fastcompany.com/3042326/tech-forecast/with-500000-users-slack-says-its-the-fastest-growing-business-app-ever&quot; title=&quot;Fast Company article about Slack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;quickly becoming a communication standard&lt;/a&gt; among companies and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re excited to announce the launch of a Slack Community for &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; Barcelona startups and entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;https://bcnstartup.typeform.com/to/YV0pu1&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Slack Community&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to join the Barcelona Startup community!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the success Slack found in companies, communities are now embracing Slack as a tool to engage with their current members and attract new ones. Communities such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://nomadlist.com/&quot; title=&quot;Nomad List&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Nomad List&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rubyonrails.link/&quot; title=&quot;Ruby on Rails community&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt; are some of the best examples of online Slack communities. There are some great individuals compiling lists of Slack communities, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@angiecois/an-incomplete-list-of-communities-on-slack-1b1b6f157bda&quot; title=&quot;An incomplete list of communities on Slack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this one created by Angela Cois&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why Slack?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffer wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.bufferapp.com/slack-community&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&#39;s guide to Slack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;a very useful guide about how to create a Slack community&lt;/a&gt;, highlighting the advantages of bringing everyone together. This way, purely offline communities can now become online, while other online-based communities, can use Slack to offer a new level of interaction among their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us, Slack&amp;#39;s market share is the main reason why we chose it as our app of choice, thus minimising the cost of adopting a new tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack also supports multi-team sign-in. So if you are using Slack with your team, you can quickly switch to another one with a keyboard shortcut. In the following picture you can see my Slack (notice the left bar, where each icon is a Slack team):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post25a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Slack&#39;s multi-team support&quot; title=&quot;Slack&#39;s multi-team support&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;I&amp;#39;m on 9 teams! Nine interesting teams just a keyboard shortcut away!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Slack has got really cool mobile apps. You can chat from your phone or tablet, from wherever you are, irrespective of the device you&amp;#39;re using. This is a fundamental feature for a distributed team like MarsBased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack also offers a huge flexibility on how to use it. Pinned documents, search, mentions, file sharing, integrations with dozens of interesting services and other killer features make Slack a safe bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our community can grow to have hundreds (or even thousands!) of members without having to worry about the scalability of this platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How will we use it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our main goal is to become the largest Slack community in Barcelona for entrepreneurs &amp;amp; startups. We will connect entrepreneurs that want to help each other and share relevant content &lt;strong&gt;in real time&lt;/strong&gt; with the different communities in Barcelona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will start rolling out to the Startup Grind members today and like-minded companies &amp;amp; individuals. We want to open it up to the whole Barcelona startup community shortly afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Slack, we are able to bring the communication between community members to another level. For instance, at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupgrind.com/barcelona&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Grind Barcelona&lt;/a&gt; we offer the first hour of the event to our attendees, and we call it the &lt;i&gt;Community Hour&lt;/i&gt;. In our Open Mic session, between 15 and 20 entrepreneurs per event come on stage to ask help for their projects and offer their services in return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our attendees have asked/offered very different things during the Open Mic: a cofounder, a CTO, investment, some growth hacking ideas, mentoring and even translators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post25b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Open Mic at Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; title=&quot;Open Mic at Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Our friend Michael from Miniguide.es rocking the stage during our Open Mic!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we created a channel to move this interesting exchange online, so you don&amp;#39;t have to wait for the next event! You will never miss that interesting person who spoke at the Open Mic, but you didn&amp;#39;t get to talk to. You can find them in our Slack community!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example: our attendees can also send questions in real time to the speaker during the fireside chat, or live-comment the interview and/or the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we will grow the number of users, we will listen to what they want, and adapt the Slack community to them. If they want a channel to offer jobs, or to bring in a new community, or engage with influencers, or any other need, we will try to meet their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How can you use it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to benefit with this online Startup community. We&amp;#39;re bringing immediate solutions to startups and freelancers alike, who way too often require immediate ideas or resources to complete the tasks at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;re a couple of clicks away of asking for help in the general channel, comment an event on its corresponding channel, send a private message to that designer freelancer to hire him or just to chat a lazy Sunday away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will also use this Slack community to promote your cool stuff. Oftentimes, too many projects go unnoticed, so a good way to give your stuff more visibility is by being among the early adopters of a new tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Share your blog posts, your startup&amp;#39;s job openings, your events or your latest logo design through this platform. There are endless possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Community Giveback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased, we feel very attached to the Barcelona entrepreneurial community. Not only did we run for almost two years the &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/09/21/Five-Reasons-Why-Your-Company-Should-Organise-an-Event/&quot; title=&quot;Startup Circle, by MarsBased&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Circle&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MarsBased/status/391521920858214400&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased Tweet about Startup Circle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&amp;#39;s our tweet announcing it back then!&lt;/a&gt;) but we&amp;#39;re also behind Startup Grind Barcelona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Startup Circle, we brought together a community of 50 individuals &amp;amp; companies that met once or twice a month to help one another and socialise. That was our door to entrepreneurship, and we hope it has helped other people as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since March 2014, we&amp;#39;re also running Startup Grind in Barcelona, with the help of some brilliant people such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://startupgrind.cat/contact/&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind team&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Carlos Cruz, Alex Gonzalez and a team of volunteers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this Slack community, we want to give back to the community that helped us grow when we started. This is especially important for global companies like ours that want to help foster business opportunities in their area. At MarsBased, we like to contribute back to the Barcelona startup scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you interested in joining the Barcelona Startup Slack community? You can do it by clicking &lt;a href=&quot;https://bcnstartup.typeform.com/to/YV0pu1&quot; title=&quot;Barcelona Startup Slack Community&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2015 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/10/26/We-Launched-Slack-For-The-Barcelona-Startup-Community</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/10/26/We-Launched-Slack-For-The-Barcelona-Startup-Community</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Code Refactoring: When, Why and Who</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d365.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of tech companies has caused a higher adoption of technology among new generations. People are learning how to code in order to keep up with the times, or to reinvent themselves professionally to unlock new paths in their career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more we code, the more we need to make it a sustainable practice. Quantity almost never implies quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter code refactoring. Everyone talks about &lt;i&gt;what&lt;/i&gt; refactoring is, and &lt;i&gt;how&lt;/i&gt; to do it, but we want to talk about the other three dimensions: when to do it, why, and who should do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a target=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_refactoring&quot; title=&quot;Code refactoring&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;Code refactoring is the process of restructuring existing computer code – changing the factoring – without changing its external behavior. Refactoring improves nonfunctional attributes of the software&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are the CTO of a recently-founded dev shop: sitting in front of your laptop, fingers ready to code, while waiting for your salesman to bring in the contract for the next Facebook. However, the first project happens to come with legacy. That is, a client hires your company to fix an already existing project, which unsurprisingly is broken. The first five words that come to mind are: &amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;I can do this better!&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, at MarsBased, a very large proportion of our existing clients had a different provider in the past, but they decided to change for different reasons. This is something we learnt during &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/04/13/Lessons-Learned-One-Year-Running-Our-Own-Business/&quot;&gt;our first year operating&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you being able to rewrite better code may actually be true, you should also consider the client&amp;#39;s needs. Why did this project end up on your table? Maybe the quality of the deliverables was insufficient, or maybe because the client perceived the development team&amp;#39;s pace was very low and he was running out of patience (and cash).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having that in mind, it will probably take longer to start from scratch, and rebuild everything instead of replacing the existing code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we decide? We do it case by case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coding by the fireplace&quot; title=&quot;Coding by the fireplace&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;In this entry, we&amp;#39;re talking about code refactoring: when, why and who. If we were to talk about the where, it would probably be here.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The When&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the application is too big, a whole refactor can take ages. It will also be impossible to rebuild it while maintaining the strict deadlines the market or the investors dictate. On the other hand, if the application is small enough, you might also get distracted by too much refactoring instead of adding new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our customers hire us to give answers. If the code we find in legacy projects is not good, we tell them. We can also audit the code and provide a report with the cost of rebuilding everything or opting for a complete refactor. Most of the times, though, the clients want to keep up with the ongoing development while adopting a progressive refactoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us, &lt;i&gt;progressive refactoring&lt;/i&gt; is sticking to the development roadmap and its new features, while improving the existing code with each release. When we need to touch legacy code, our commitment is to &lt;i&gt;leave it better than before&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By applying this, you will find that the application progressively looks and feels way better, without affecting the releases roadmap and the product evolution. This is extremely important in projects that have already launched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there&amp;#39;s more than that. The fight for the &lt;i&gt;Greater Code&lt;/i&gt; is better fought with tests. The quality of tests (or lack thereof) in legacy projects is a game-changer. Refactoring the tests is as important as refactoring the code. But again, you will have to agree with the client the deadlines &amp;amp; deliverables, and the time devoted to refactoring and testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refactoring is a time investment: you devote time now to make it easier to work on it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Why&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having explained when we should refactor, now it is the time to say the reason why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;New is always better&lt;/i&gt;&amp;quot; may sound great, but old code can save you time. While it may be outdated, or even not work, it is the result of somebody else&amp;#39;s effort to solve a specific problem, and their approach could be really different from yours. So you can still learn a lot from other people&amp;#39;s code before throwing it away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since our approach is to leave code better than we found it, we always try to understand the existing code in order to improve it. It might even contain a solution you would have never come across!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, bad code tends to replicate itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s be honest: we &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; copy and paste code. Although we ought not to do it, we borrow code often to either save time or solve complexities beyond our skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we should replace bad code when we find it. By eliminating bad code, we eliminate the chance of somebody borrowing those parts for other projects. This is even more so important when introducing new hires or less-experienced programmers to the project: they might think that code is yours or, worse, perceive it as a reference and replicate it somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our CTO, Xavi, &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2014/08/22/The-Martians-conquer-the-IronHack/&quot;&gt; gave a talk at Ironhack a year ago&lt;/a&gt; where he talked about the maintainability of the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, we need to refactor code to improve code quality, maintainability and legibility, while making it easier for other teammates to become familiar with the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Who&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We strongly believe refactoring is good for everybody, but &lt;i&gt;who&lt;/i&gt; should do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refactoring forces you to think over a piece of code that somebody else wrote trying to solve a difficulty. It might as well be code you wrote in another company or even years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased, all of us refactor code from the very first day. We&amp;#39;re given the style guide and instructed to produce quality code right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When introducing a new team member to a project, it is a good practice to make him refactor the code. This way, he does not only become familiar with the project, but we&amp;#39;re weaseling in some good practices we seldom might find time for. By touching code here and there, we&amp;#39;re forced to swim through the different layers &amp;amp; components until we get the whole picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Junior developers have more room to learn, and sharing your refactoring tools with them will make them grow as developers in the right direction. They are also less prone to have any bad habits acquired throughout the years, and tend to write code the way they read it. They may also need a senior developer to guide them through the process in the beginning, but soon enough they develop the habit of writing healthy code. Once again, time invested in mentoring a junior developer will pay off threefold in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time goes by, the initiated developers will feel more confident in their coding skills, and they will start suggesting changes and improvements on other people&amp;#39;s code. A self-confident developer will be far more independent taking decisions that will benefit the project. All thanks to a good learning process through guidance and demanding quality from the get-go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only have we got a commitment towards the clients to deliver quality code, but with the established deadlines and the product roadmap. These are a couple of ways how we align with our clients&amp;#39; business model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s your experience on refactoring from day zero? Have you ever tried it? Would you add other Whys Whens or Whos? If you have any thoughts on the subject feel free to share them using the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/10/05/Code-Refactoring-When-Why-And-Who</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/10/05/Code-Refactoring-When-Why-And-Who</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Five Reasons Why Your Company Should Organise an Event</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d352.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After over a year and a half organising the &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2013/11/07/startup-circle-barcelona&quot; title=&quot;Startup Circle in Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Circle in Barcelona&lt;/a&gt;, we decided to pull the plug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been hosting Startup Circle and &lt;a href=&quot;http://startupgrind.com/barcelona&quot; title=&quot;Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Grind&lt;/a&gt; until we realised they shared the same dynamics and principles: educating, inspiring and connecting entrepreneurs by helping each other. Therefore, we decided to merge the two communities to take Startup Grind BCN to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through all these months, we have learnt the following benefits of organising events as a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. It broadens your networks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By organising an event, you will have to contact different sorts of companies than those on your sales funnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your event might require sponsors to help you with the expenses, or companies willing to pay for the catering or beverages in exchange for exposure and presence in the event. This is your entry point to a whole new set of potential clients or partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on what kind of event you&amp;#39;re planning, you might also need good speakers or celebrities to attract bigger audiences. By inviting them to an event, you have an excuse to shoot an email to that big guy and start a conversation. This might eventually bring some unexpected business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you bring value to all the new contacts you make, and all else will follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post23a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Thanking sponsors at Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; title=&quot;Thanking sponsors at Startup Grind Barcelona&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;At Startup Grind Barcelona first anniversary, we had our sponsors&amp;#39; logos in front of 180 people. Who doesn&amp;#39;t want that?&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. It gives you media exposure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though there are lots of events going on, events are like startups: most of them fail. Therefore, we recommend waiting before you pitch the press too early. Instead, try building a solid event before marketing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People in the press, bloggers, social media influencers and media-friendly individuals are usually busy people who get lots of invitations to check out the latest cool event in town. Try making their life easier by waiting until your event is really valuable to invite them over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will appreciate your patience, and your event will be good enough for them to like it and write about it. Some of them will come back in the next edition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting with the first point, this will also open doors in the press and media community. Use them wisely, as some of them are one-off shots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. You will be recognised as an expert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every company or individual in business has a target customer. We are used to bombing our target customers by sending them our services brochures, newsletters or project quotes. We are usually too &lt;em&gt;direct&lt;/em&gt; in our sales process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few people can think differently about this and give real value to the customer before thinking about money. We have seen companies or freelancers offering free e-books or webinars to attract new clients. This is giving before taking, which is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cio.com/article/2867406/marketing/how-to-use-ebooks-to-improve-your-content-marketing-strategy.html&quot; title=&quot;Ebooks increase sales&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt; proven way to increase your sales&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should try to cater your potential customers with an event for them. Listen to their necessities and build the event around them. What do they want? Workshops? Inspirational stories? Quality networking? An informal meeting to drink beer with like-minded people? Something they can sponsor to get exposure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, you might not be the expert in the room, but you&amp;#39;re the one making things happen. You are organising an event regularly, thus creating value in the community. This will help people think of you when looking for an expert in your field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, if you can bring together dozens - or hundreds - of people in the same room regularly, with some experts here and there, that means you know &lt;em&gt;a thing or two&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;4. Offline is the new online&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, not having online presence was business suicide. When Internet became more accessible worldwide, all companies transitioned to the web and the first movers had a head start on the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, we think that being &lt;em&gt;offline&lt;/em&gt; can really boost your success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As technology made it easier for everybody to put up a sharp-looking landing page, using services like About.me, Strikingly or Squarespace, credibility is now at stake. If everybody can afford that, how can we be sure that the people behind those websites are legitimate/a big company/a full time consultant/a quality provider? The answer is clear: by meeting them in real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might look contradictory that a remote working company is telling you to do business in person, but that&amp;#39;s human nature. Physical presence breeds trust, as stated by &lt;a href=&quot;http://realbusiness.co.uk/article/26202-building-trust-is-all-important-when-doing-business-online&quot; title=&quot;Interview to Tobias Kormind&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Tobias Kormind, manager of 77 Diamonds&lt;/a&gt;. Build up trust in real life, then move to the online world once the business happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5. People will help you&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could not wrap up this blog entry without underlining how great it is to meet new people, and here&amp;#39;s our way to thank them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post23b.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Enjoying a cold one after work with Startup Circle&quot; title=&quot;Enjoying a cold one after work with Startup Circle&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;With our friends from Dineyo, Nektria, Rockyourmeal and the rest of Startup Circle in one of our after-work events.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your event is genuine enough, people will sympathise with it. Some of them will tweet about it, share it on their social profiles, while some others will help you with a connection or two. You can even get people volunteer for you if they see the real value in the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your event should be your way of giving back to the community that saw you start up your business. It is not only an act of kindness, but your community will genuinely benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our experience and, of course, we will like to complement it with your insight. Do you also organise events? Are you an expert on the matter? Feel free to share what you have learnt so far in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/09/21/Five-Reasons-Why-Your-Company-Should-Organise-an-Event</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/09/21/Five-Reasons-Why-Your-Company-Should-Organise-an-Event</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Create a Blogging Strategy for Your Company</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain&amp;#39;s log, stardate d317.y36/AB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been blogging for some time now, and we’ve learnt a thing or two. Because we’ve adopted transparency as an integral part of the company culture, we like sharing what we learn with you. It’s a genuine way to give back to the community that has helped so much become what we are now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this entry, we will cover how to create a blogging strategy for your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re really proud of how and what we blog, because it helps us keeping track of our evolution as a global development shop, and feel like this could prove useful to many others that come after us. Exactly the same way we learnt from others like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buffer.com&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Buffer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dockyard.com&quot; title=&quot;Dockyard&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Dockyard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thoughtbot.com&quot; title=&quot;Thoughtbot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Thoughtbot&lt;/a&gt; or other blogs we follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago we published the &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2015/05/05/The-MarsBased-Blogging-Guide/&quot; title=&quot;The MarsBased Blogging Guide pt.1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;first part of our blogging guide&lt;/a&gt;. In the first part, we described how to craft a good blog post, by choosing a good title, the appropriate keywords, a fitting image, and other important criteria bloggers follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogging is nowadays a very important element in growing your company: it is one of the cheapest methods to create &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inbound_marketing&quot; title=&quot;Definition of Inbound Marketing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;inbound marketing&lt;/a&gt;, provides SEO, and helps you demonstrate your expertise to a very large audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this second part, we’re going to describe how to choose a blogging strategy for your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Choose a goal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, one must identify what is the purpose of his/her blog. A blog can be a good tool to publish news about your company, how-to guides, inspirational stories, funny viral content or almost whatever you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most common uses is content marketing. In this case, companies blog about the topics they want to be identified with and thus, they create new content for their site on a frequent basis. This content, in turn, attracts potential customers to their sales funnel. Google and most search engines like original content that updates regularly, hence being blogs a most useful tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MarsBased we use it to drive qualified traffic to our website, so we made it a key element in our sales toolset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we created the company, we didn’t have that much of a strategy, so we wrote posts about our company evolution: what we did and why we did it. However, some of these posts helped us rank high enough in search engines because they contained the right keywords. For instance, our most visited blog entry is &lt;a href=&quot;https://marsbased.com/blog/2014/03/25/how-we-make-the-right-app2/&quot; title=&quot;MarsBased tech stack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this one we wrote about our tech stack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have received a couple of project requests because of our post about technologies. In that post, we didn’t only show our expertise on the listed tools, but the content also made us rank higher on Google, especially in high-demanded technologies like AngularJS or Sidekiq because they’re specific enough to be very visible to the few people that google them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that brings us onto the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key question:&lt;/strong&gt; what do you want your blog to be known for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Identify your target and blog for it&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve selected the purpose of your blog, you need to choose the audience. Who will read your blog?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, chances are you will want the whole world to read your blog from the get-go. However, it is a nearly impossible task to bring a generic blog to big audiences by making it grow organically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your target audience is the whole world, you are probably doing something wrong. You’d better hire somebody skilled in growth-hacking, or use paid marketing strategies (SEM) to achieve rapid growth. But we will not be covering this scenario in our guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A safer way is to choose a very defined audience and go for it. For instance, if your product is a fitness app, you should blog about fitness, nutrition and healthy lifestyles to attract your target audience: nutritionists, people that want to get fit, gym rats, personal trainers, and the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case, we want to build trust with companies we haven’t met yet and attract potential clients, by proving our expertise in web development. Therefore, we are sharing how we work, what we do, and things that are interesting to C-level personnel, our entry point in most companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining a target audience will also help you choose the kind of content and the language level. You can blog about marketing for the CMOs, tech stuff for CTOs and productivity for CEOs. Having multiple targets or multiple topics is not less effective, so long as it is part of your business strategy and you cater all of them accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the language, technical posts might have technicisms, but it does not hurt to explain the acronyms or lead the reader somewhere where he/she can find the definitions (e.g: &amp;quot;If you don’t know what Inbound Marketing is, read this post over here…”). The more specific your target audience is, the more niche keywords you are allowed to use. Elsewise, if you’re targeting a massive audience, you will have to use very high-level and generic language, avoiding all sorts of acronyms, technical words or jargon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key question&lt;/strong&gt;: What readers do you want to engage with through your blog and what do you need of them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Define your topics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have chosen your goal and your audience, you must identify what will be interesting to your target readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best blogs often cover just one specific topic. It might be travel, entrepreneurship, productivity, cuisine or knitting. But some blogs cover many topics to attract different sorts of target readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re bootstrapping a company, you will most likely neither have the time to blog, nor the resources to have somebody do that for you. A good tip is to start small by covering a single topic. For instance, our buddies at &lt;a href=&quot;https://getquipu.com/en&quot; title=&quot;Quipu&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Quipu&lt;/a&gt;, a personal finances app (built using Ruby on Rails!), chose to target small companies and freelancers/contractors that want to automate their bookkeeping. As a result of that, they are &lt;a href=&quot;http://getquipu.com/blog/&quot; title=&quot;Quipu Blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;blogging about personal finances&lt;/a&gt;: how to do paperwork, how-to guides on taxes &amp;amp; forms, common mistakes in bookkeeping and tips about saving money on taxes are some of the topics they’ve dealt with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might look obvious, but if you write about startups and entrepreneurship, don&amp;#39;t review your most favourite restaurants. It&amp;#39;s OK to go offtopic every once in a while, but not every second post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line here is that choosing the right topics attracts like-minded people, it’ll rank great in Google and you can share it in niche groups or publications to be exposed to a larger audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key question:&lt;/strong&gt; What field(s) is your company most proficient in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Measure your tempo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a common mistake to start writing a blog with nothing to publish. Most people build up a few posts before launching the blog so that they can publish stacked posts for the first weeks, without having to worry about running out of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if you’re really committed to writing frequently, chances are, in your first blog you’ll write very effusively for some time and then will stop after a few weeks. That is why you should include the posting frequency in your strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is better to define a frequency and follow it strictly. For instance, at MarsBased we decided to post once a month a while back ago, and since earlier this year we’ve achieved it. Now we plan to blog twice a month to include a technical post, and a non-technical post to cater our different targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good advice is to define a minimum, never a fixed number. It is better to say “I will post at least once every fortnight” than “I will publish 3 posts a month”. This way, if you&amp;#39;re really prolific one month, you can go over your goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you grow your company, you will also want to grow your content team. Likewise, depending on how important is the blog to your goals, you will increase the number of posts per month/week/day at a sustainable pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few variations of the sentence “Content is king”. We’d like to add our bit to it: “Content is king, constancy is queen”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key question:&lt;/strong&gt; How often can you afford making your blog your first priority?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Pick a date &amp;amp; time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have defined your blog frequency, you need to select what days &amp;amp; times are better for your readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, you should take into account your timezone. Say, if you’re an offshoring development company from India and your target is the UK, try posting in their morning, so that people read your blog first thing during breakfast or during their commute to work. Also, companies targeting US clients should choose between East &amp;amp; West Coast. A good tactic is to publish for East Coast first, and then publish the link in the social networks for each different time zone you might have defined as target (West Coast, Japan, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://buffer.com&quot; title=&quot;Buffer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Buffer&lt;/a&gt; and other social media gurus, the best time to blog is either early in the morning or right after lunch. There does not seem to be a consensus on which days of the week are better for blogging. Test it for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test, measure, repeat. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/analytics/&quot; title=&quot;Google Analytics&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://medium.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Medium&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; and many Wordpress plugins are really effective when measuring the impact of your blog posts. By using them, you can understand your audience and adjust your publishing times to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key question:&lt;/strong&gt; When are your target readers most prone to devote some time to read you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Produce content worth sharing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t really know a lot about how to monetise a blog, so this tip goes to bloggers that want to get exposure organically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our favourite social media gurus, Guy Kawasaki, explained what is the most effective tactic to be noticed on social networks. His advice is to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.startupgrind.com/events/details/startup-grind-london-hosted-guy-kawasaki-canvaex-apple#/&quot; title=&quot;Guy Kawasaki at Startup Grind&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;create content worth sharing&lt;/a&gt;. Your content can be inspiring, educational, fun, viral, give free content or what have you, but it should really get your audience to spread the word for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is your friend and can really boost your number of views and shares: aim for retweets or shareable content. Not only will the entry be good, but you can also test stuff outside of the content. For instance, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.bufferapp.com/a-scientific-guide-to-writing-great-headlines-on-twitter-facebook-and-your-blog&quot; title=&quot;Buffer Blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Buffer test their blog posts titles using the social networks&lt;/a&gt;. They share each blog entry with three or four different titles and perform A/B testing. The tweet that gets more visits, retweets, likes and favourites is the best title for the blog. This is only a way to A/B test it, but there are millions of ideas out there! Be creative!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social networks also offer a great chance to engage with your community. For those old enough to have used internet forums back when they were the thing - in the pre-Google or pre-Myspace days - we saw people posting stuff in forums to get like-minded people’s opinion and interesting discussions. You can do the same here, by wrapping up the post with a call to action, as we said in the first part of our blogging guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also learn a lot from Instagram, where famous Instagrammers ask to “tag a friend” when that photo relates to them in any way. Hence, we can ask our friends or colleagues to comment on a post we wrote if we think it applies to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key question:&lt;/strong&gt; if you read this blog entry somewhere else, would you share it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Content must be educational and inspiring&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that works very well for me, when I am looking for new ideas, is to read a lot of blogs. From there, I always spot one or two blog entries that catch my attention and I want to mimic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, CartoDB’s entry of &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@saleiva/how-we-hire-3e696c3aee59&quot; title=&quot;CartoDB Medium&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“How we hire”&lt;/a&gt; inspired Pablo Villalba’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://micho.biz/post/117083319566/how-we-hire&quot; title=&quot;Pablo Villalba Blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“How we hire”&lt;/a&gt; and, in turn, inspired me to include it in our Article Ideas board on Trello.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/post22a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Our blog ideas on Trello&quot; title=&quot;Our blog ideas on Trello&quot; class=&quot;img-center img-rounded img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-footer&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;We&amp;#39;ve got a Trello board for our blog posts.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These posts were inspirational: not only do they make me want to write something similar for MarsBased, but they might also inspire us to adopt some new tools, strategies or techniques in our daily routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side, the content needs to be also useful and teach you something new. It must educate. This is especially so for companies like ours that want to prove their technical skills before they get hired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good examples of educational blog posts are &lt;a href=&quot;https://robots.thoughtbot.com/a-case-study-in-multiple-time-zones&quot; title=&quot;Thoughtbot blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dockyard.com/blog/2015/07/31/taking-advantage-of-time-limitations-in-design&quot; title=&quot;Dockyard blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://chopdawg.com/managing-company-remotely/&quot; title=&quot;Chopdawg blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, and we’re pretty sure they have helped those companies to earn a few more leads by demonstrating their expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key question:&lt;/strong&gt; What are your favourite blogs and why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Make it visible&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One tremendous mistake bloggers make is not letting the world know they have a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come on, you’ve spent time setting up a blog, creating a brand for it - if not company -, researching, writing content, picking nice images, tweaking its look &amp;amp; feel, selecting the keywords and all these chores, yet you don’t tell every soul about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things you can do:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update all your social media profiles to link to your blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add it to your LinkedIn profile in the “URLs” section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join blog listings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post your content in LinkedIn/Google+/Facebook groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automate your social network accounts to publish automatically every new entry using tools like IFTTT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask famous people on Twitter to retweet you (do it only if the content relates to them).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add it to your signature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key question:&lt;/strong&gt; Where do you want your blog to get noticed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations if you have made it this far. Now it&amp;#39;s time to define your strategy and blog your way to success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us know if we have missed something in our comments section!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/08/16/How-to-Create-a-Blogging-Strategy-for-your-Company</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.marsbased.com/blog/2015/08/16/How-to-Create-a-Blogging-Strategy-for-your-Company</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>